Welcome to the fifth session
of our “Pursue Peace”! Convention,
「平和をつくる」地区大会の
3日目午前の部に
which corresponds to the Sunday
morning session on your program.
ようこそおいでくださいました
Our music-video presentation
is about to begin.
まずミュージックビデオを
楽しみましょう
神との平和な関係を築くなら
幸せになれる ということが分かります
As you watch,
please notice how pursuing peace
with God brings great happiness.
どうぞお楽しみください
Please enjoy the presentation!
兄弟姉妹 こんにちは
Greetings, brothers and sisters!
3日目の主題は
ローマ 15:13に基づいています
The scripture theme
for this session and the next
is taken from the inspired words
found at Romans 15:13,
「希望を与える神が⋯⋯皆さんを
which says in part:
“May the God who gives hope
あらゆる喜びと平和で
満たしてくださ［る］」というものです
fill you with all joy and peace.”
ではご一緒に 101番の賛美の歌
We invite all to sing song number 101,
「一致して共に働く」を歌いましょう
“Working Together in Unity.”
Again, that’s song number 101.
歌は101番です
私たちは時折
At times, specific challenges
can make it difficult
平和をつくるのがとても難しいと
感じることがあります
for servants of Jehovah to pursue peace.
What are these challenges,
and how can we overcome them?
どんなときでしょうか
どう対処できるでしょうか
そうした点を 7部から成る
シンポジウムで考えます
These questions will be answered
in a seven-part symposium.
平和の種をまいて平和を
刈り取った人たちの手本に
We will consider
how we can imitate the examples
of those who reaped peace
after first sowing it.
どのように倣えるかを学びます
まず 奉仕委員会の援助者
To begin, let’s give our attention
to Brother William Turner,
ウィリアム･ターナー兄弟の
話に耳を傾けましょう
a helper to the Service Committee,
as he presents the talk
主題は
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち
ヨセフと兄たち」です
—Joseph and His Brothers.”
聖書には クリスチャンが
生活の指針にできる
The Bible contains
many fundamental principles
that a Christian
can use every day to guide his life.
基本的な原則が
たくさん収められています
For example,
例えば 格言 13:20には
at Proverbs 13:20, we’re told
that if we ‘walk with wise persons,
we will become wise.’
「賢い人たちと共に歩むと
賢くな［る］」とあります
格言 28:20によると
Proverbs 28:20 states
that if ‘we’re faithful,
「忠実な人は多くの祝福を受け」ます
we will receive many blessings.’
Likely you have Bible principles
that you live by as well.
皆さんも大切にしている原則が
あることでしょう
では 平和をつくることに関しては
どうでしょうか
However, as it pertains to pursuing peace,
there is one essential principle
1つの重要な原則を
思いに留めている必要があります
that must be followed.
Let’s find out what it is.
どんな原則でしょうか
ご一緒にガラテア 6章を開きましょう
Turn with me, please, to Galatians chapter 6,
and let’s read the words
of Galatians chapter 6,
注目したいのは ガラテア 6章の
verses 7, 8.
7節と8節です
Here we read:
こうあります
「思い違いをしてはなりません
“Do not be misled:
神はご自分を侮る者を
大目に見ることはありません
“God is not one to be mocked.
“For whatever a person is sowing,
人は自分がまいているものを
必ず刈り取ることになります
“this he will also reap;
罪深い欲望のままにまいている人は
“because the one sowing
with a view to his flesh
罪深い欲望によって腐敗を刈り取り
“will reap corruption from his flesh,
聖なる力に導かれてまいている人は
“but the one sowing with a view to the spirit
聖なる力によって永遠の命を
刈り取ることになるのです」
will reap everlasting life from the spirit.”
So the principle:
原則は まいたものを
刈り取るということです
We reap what we sow.
You might think of a farmer;
農業をする人は
he knows that he must plant
what he hopes to reap.
当然 自分が刈り取りたいものの
種をまきます
そして すぐには実がならないことを
理解しています
He also knows that he will not
reap fruitage right away,
but he trusts the results
will come in due time.
でもいずれ実がなることを確信して
その時を待ちます
It is similar with the quality of peace.
平和もそれと似ています
The only way for us to reap peace
平和を刈り取るには
平和の種をまかなければなりません
is to sow it.
And as we put in the work to achieve it,
そして いずれ平和を
刈り取れることを確信し
we trust that in due time
努力しながらその時を待ちます
we will reap the benefits.
In this symposium, we will consider Bible
and modern-day accounts
このシンポジウムでは
古代や現代のエホバの民の例を考えます
of how Jehovah’s people,
despite particular challenges,
問題に直面しながらも
平和の種をまいて
刈り取った人たちの例です
have reaped peace after first sowing it.
Now, one particular challenge
to gaining peace
さて 平和を乱すものの1つに
家族間の問題があります
is problems within the family.
Because of imperfection,
不完全さのせいで
it’s not uncommon to have disagreements,
家族との関係が緊張するということが
あるかもしれません
even tension, from time to time.
互いを傷つけるようなことを言ったり
したりすることもあります
And family members may hurt one another
in various ways.
And usually such offenses are minor,
でも大抵はささいなことなので
and peace can quickly be sown and reaped.
すぐに平和の種をまいて
刈り取れるでしょう
でも もっと深刻な場合は
どうでしょうか
But what if the offense is more serious?
家族が言ったりしたりしたことのせいで
深く傷ついたとします
A family member says or does something
that hurts us deeply.
Well, even then,
そういう時でも 平和の種をまいて
it still may be possible
to sow and reap peace.
平和を刈り取ることは
不可能ではありません
We can prove this
by considering the Bible account
聖書に出てくるヨセフと兄たちの例から
そのことを考えてみましょう
of Joseph and his brothers.
よく知っている話ですね
Now, we’re familiar with the story.
Out of envy,
Joseph’s brothers sold him into slavery.
兄たちはヨセフをねたんで
奴隷として売りました
これはささいな過ちでは
ありませんでした
And this was by no means a minor offense.
ヨセフはエジプトに連れていかれます
It began with Joseph being led to Egypt.
Sometime later, he was falsely accused
and thrown into prison.
そして後に無実の罪で
牢屋に入れられます
So for 13 years,
それで 13年もの間
ヨセフはひどい目に遭いました
Joseph suffered mistreatment
when he had done nothing to deserve it.
何も悪いことをしていないのにです
ヨセフは次のように考えたでしょうか
Now, it could have been very easy
for Joseph to feel
that if he ever saw his brothers again,
「また兄たちに会えたとしても
the best option for peace
お互いの平和のために
would be not to have any dealings
with them at all.
もう一切関わりを
持たないようにしよう」
そう考えたとしても無理はありません
Perhaps we might feel the same way as well.
でもヨセフは違いました
But Joseph didn’t do that.
In fact, after some years passed,
それからしばらくたった後
ヨセフも兄たちも平和の種をまきます
both Joseph and his brothers sowed peace.
Now, note how this was done.
どうしてそうできたのか
詩編 105編を見てみましょう
Turn with me, please, to the 105th Psalm,
詩編 105編の19節を読みましょう
and note the 19th verse of Psalm 105.
It says: “Until the time
that his word proved true,
特に前半の言葉に注目したいと思います
“the saying of Jehovah
「エホバの言葉が彼を磨き上げた」
is what refined him.”
ヨセフはエホバに磨き上げていただき
Joseph trusted in Jehovah to refine him,
エホバに倣った考え方や
振る舞い方を心掛けました
to shape his thinking and godly qualities.
He refused to become bitter.
憤りを抱きませんでした
In fact, how interesting it is to note
ヨセフが兄たちに
ひどい目に遭わされたと
that there is nothing
in the Scriptures to indicate
誰かに話したというようなことは
聖書のどこにも書かれていません
that Joseph ever told anyone,
not even Pharaoh,
ファラオにさえ
自分が兄たちに
奴隷として売られたということは
that his brothers were the ones
who kidnapped him and sold him as a slave.
話さなかったようです
And how about Joseph’s brothers?
兄たちはどうでしたか
Years after they had mistreated him,
they met Joseph in Egypt.
何年もたってから
エジプトでヨセフに会います
ヨセフはわざと末の弟である
ベニヤミンをひいきして
When Joseph tested them
by giving the youngest brother, Benjamin,
significantly more attention
than he gave the others,
兄たちを試しました
でも兄たちは変化していました
he saw that his brothers had changed.
人をねたまなくなっていたのです
They had let go of envy.
They showed genuine concern for their brother
弟や父親ヤコブのことを
深く気遣っていました
and for their father, Jacob.
Joseph realized
that his brothers were repentant,
ヨセフは兄たちが悔い改めたのを見て
and he forgave them.
許しました
And because Joseph and his brothers
were willing to take steps to sow peace,
ヨセフも兄たちも
平和の種をまくように努力したので
they reaped the benefits
とても良い結果を
刈り取ることができました
and eventually were able to enjoy
また家族として
仲良く暮らすことができたのです
a harmonious relationship.
Well, how can the example
of Joseph and his brothers
このヨセフと兄たちの例から
何を学べるでしょうか
help us today?
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオの中で
どのように平和の種が
まかれたかに注目しましょう
notice how a family member sows peace.
And every morning
ジェレミーは毎朝 本当に毎朝
—and I mean every morning—
there’s Jeremy singing
at the top of his lungs.
すっごく大きな声で歌ってたんだ
いや 僕だけじゃないよ
OK, I wasn’t the only one.
No, but you were the loudest.
そうだけど でも一番大きかったよ
兄さん いつもそういうこと
ばっかり言う
Spoken like a true big brother.
I was always impressed
with how close you two were.
2人は本当にいつも仲がいいですよね
Hmm.
うん でも
Well, it wasn’t always that way.
そうじゃないときもあった
No.
うん でも もともと仲は良かったんだ
I mean, it started out that way.
Nick and I—we weren’t just brothers;
兄と弟というよりは
we were friends.
友達だった
But then the family business
ran into trouble,
うちは家族で仕事をしてたんだけど
and what started
as a small disagreement just exploded.
問題が起きて
ささいなことから口論になった
You don’t even understand at all
how our business works!
おまえはうちの仕事の流れが
全く分かってないんだ！
Instead of criticizing,
could you just once . . .
批判ばっかりしないで
一度くらいこっちのことも・・・
Jeremy!
ジェレミー！
Do you have any idea
what this is going to cost us?
これ どれだけ
コストかかるか分かってんのか？
しょうがないだろ
こっちは聞いてなかったんだから
I didn’t have a choice.
You went behind my back!
What’s your problem?
足引っ張んなよ！
You!
You’re the problem.
引っ張ってるのは兄さんだろ！
We tried to work it out.
仲良くやろうと努力した
But things just got worse.
でも 悪くなる一方だった
It was like a door
had slammed shut between us.
2人の間に厚い壁を感じた
On the outside,
I acted like everything was fine.
人前では普通に振る舞っていた
But inside, I couldn’t let it go.
でも 心の中では全然許していなかった
I felt like a total hypocrite,
自分が偽善者のように感じた
and that had to change.
このままじゃいけないと思った
I needed a lot of help from Jehovah
エホバの助けがどうしても必要だった
to let go
—to move on—
心から許して
and make things right with Nick.
ニックと仲直りするために
傷が癒えるには時間がかかった
It took a long time
for the wounds to heal . . .
. . . and for us to trust each other
the way we used to.
以前のように
信頼し合えるようになるにも
But we did.
でも仲直りできた
平和な関係を取り戻せて本当に良かった
I’m so grateful that we made peace
before the world turned upside down.
世界が大変なことになる前に
では どうすればヨセフと
兄たちに倣えるでしょうか
So how can you and I
imitate Joseph and his brothers?
Let’s discuss three steps.
3つの点を考えましょう
最初の点は
エフェソス 4章の32節にあります
The first step is found at Ephesians 4:32.
読んでみましょう
Let’s read that
—Ephesian 4:32:
エフェソス 4:32
「親切な人になり
“But become kind to one another,
温かい思いやりを示し合い
“tenderly compassionate,
freely forgiving one another
神がキリストによって
寛大に許してくださったように
“just as God also by Christ
freely forgave you.”
寛大に許し合いましょう」
1つ目に 人を寛大に
許す必要があります
So first, we must be ready to forgive.
もし憤りや恨みの気持ちを
募らせてしまうなら
If we let grievances and resentment build up
and develop in our hearts,
it becomes even more difficult
to be forgiving.
許すのが難しくなることでしょう
Did you note in the video that what started
as a small disagreement
ビデオの中で ニックとジェレミーは
ささいなことがきっかけで口論になり
between Nick and Jeremy exploded
into something much bigger?
深刻な仲たがいへと発展しました
Why?
なぜでしょうか
ジェレミーが兄のニックに対して
憤りを抱き続けたからです
Jeremy could not let go
of his resentment toward his brother.
We must work to treat others
in a forgiving way,
エホバが寛大に許してくださるように
私たちも人を許さなければなりません
just as Jehovah treats us.
2つ目の点は
The second step:
Don’t dwell on the offense.
いつまでも根に持たないことです
格言 17:9には
Proverbs 17:9 says:
“The one who keeps harping on a matter
「くどくど言う人は親友を引き離す」と
書かれています
separates close friends.”
And isn’t that how Jeremy described
the relationship with his brother?
ジェレミーもそういう
状態になっていましたね
It was a door slammed shut between them.
兄との間に壁を感じていました
It wasn’t until steps were taken to sow peace
でも 平和の種をまくように
努力しました
—having that open, honest communication
with each other;
兄と腹を割って話し合うようにし
共に時間を過ごし
一緒に奉仕もしました
spending time together;
working with each other in the ministry—
only then did things start to improve.
それでやっと2人の仲が改善されました
And did you notice?
とはいえ
Everything did not go back
to normal right away.
すぐに元通りにはなりませんでしたね
It took time to reap peace,
2人が心の傷を癒やして
再び信頼し合うには
time for those wounds to heal,
time to regain lost trust.
かなりの時間が必要でした
すぐに成果を期待せず
So we can’t look for miracles,
じっくり取り組むことが大切です
but we should look for progress.
Like the farmer, trust that in due time
農業をする人のように
実がなるのを辛抱強く待って
努力するなら
we will see results from our efforts.
いずれ平和を刈り取ることが
できるでしょう
では3つ目のとても重要な点です
And here’s where
the all-important third step comes in:
憤りの気持ちを
捨て去ることができるように
Ask Jehovah in prayer
to help us to let go of resentment.
エホバに助けを祈り求めます
ヨセフのことを思い出してください
Remember Psalm 105:19.
It was “the saying of Jehovah”
that helped refine Joseph
詩編 105:19にあったように
「エホバの言葉」に助けられ
磨き上げられたので
to develop the qualities needed
not to become bitter
憤りを捨て去ることができました
and to let go of any resentment.
In the video, Jeremy acknowledged
that he needed Jehovah’s help
ビデオの中で ジェレミーも
エホバの助けのおかげで
ニックを心から許して
仲直りすることができました
to let go and to move on.
エホバは私たちも助けてくれます
And Jehovah can do the same for us.
It’s not easy when we go through situations
that threaten the peace of our family.
家族との平和な関係が
損なわれると つらいものです
でも まいたものを刈り取るという
原則を思いに留めて
But if we live by this fundamental principle
—we reap what we sow—
平和の種をまきましょう
先ほど考えたように 寛大に許し
then we can be assured
that with a forgiving spirit,
いつまでも根に持たないようにし
looking for opportunities to sow peace,
and beseeching Jehovah for his help
エホバに助けを求めるなら
our efforts will be blessed
その努力は祝福されます
and, in due time, we and our family
can reap the benefits
そしてきっと 平和を刈り取って
家族で仲良く
幸せに暮らせることでしょう
and enjoy true peace.
Brother Ronald Curzan,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
次に 教育委員会の援助者
ロナルド･カーザン兄弟が
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—The Gibeonites.”
ギベオンの人たち」という話をします
There is a battle
that has lasted for centuries
はるか昔から今に至るまでずっと
and continues down to our day.
ある対立が続いてきました
It’s a battle of wills
どんな対立でしょうか
—the will of disobedient humans
不従順な人間たちが
エホバの意志に逆らってきたのです
who fight against Jehovah’s will.
Rather than submitting
or surrendering their will
多くの人たちがエホバの
望まれることを行おうとせず
to do Jehovah’s will, most humans refuse
エホバと和解することを拒んで
to make peace with him,
becoming peacebreakers.
平和を壊してきました
On the other hand,
一方で 歴史を通じて大勢が
millions throughout the centuries
喜んでエホバの望まれることを行い
have humbly submitted to Jehovah’s will,
making his will their will.
エホバの考えに合わせてきました
その人たちは平和をつくってきたのです
They are known as peacemakers.
By sowing peace with Jehovah,
その人たちは平和の種をまいて
they have reaped the benefits of having
a close, personal friendship with him
エホバとの親しい平和な関係を
刈り取ってきました
and the wonderful hope of living forever
in a peaceful new world.
新しい平和な世界で
永遠に生きる希望も持っています
Even so, we must admit
とはいえ 時として エホバからの
指示を受け入れて従うことを
that it can be difficult at times to accept
難しく感じることがあるかもしれません
and then follow Jehovah’s direction
それにはエホバの組織からの
指示も含まれます
or direction that we may receive
from his organization,
especially if we don’t understand
the reasons behind the direction
指示の理由がよく分からなかったり
自分の考えと違ったりすると
or it’s not what we might prefer.
特に難しく感じるものです
What is needed to sow and reap peace?
平和を刈り取るには何が必要でしょうか
Humility.
謙遜さです
Humility is defined as a “lowliness of mind,
謙遜さとは 自分を低く見ることであり
freedom from pride or arrogance.”
傲慢さが全くないことです
A humble person is not self-willed,
謙遜な人は 自分の
したいようにしようとはせず
but they actively look for ways to sow peace
エホバや他の人たちと
平和な関係でいることを優先します
with Jehovah and others.
いつも平和をつくるようにするのです
He’s known as a peacemaker.
What is the result of humility
and sowing peace?
謙遜に平和の種をまくと
どんな結果になるでしょうか
Notice what Proverbs 22:4 says:
格言 22:4の言葉に注目しましょう
“The result of humility
and the fear of Jehovah
どんなものを刈り取れるでしょうか
「謙遜さとエホバへの
畏れがもたらすのは
“is [reaping, notice] riches
富と栄光と命である」
and glory and life.”
Yes, everlasting life.
そう 永遠の命です
The Bible contains many fine examples
聖書には 謙遜に
エホバの意志に従うことによって
of those who sowed and reaped peace
平和の種をまいた人たちの例が
たくさん出てきます
by humbly submitting to Jehovah’s will.
Let’s consider the example of the Gibeonites.
ギベオンの人たちの例を考えましょう
彼らは最初 イスラエル人の
敵ではなかったでしょうか
The Gibeonites
—weren’t they enemies of the Israelites?
はい
Yes.
So how did they humbly sow and reap peace
では どのように謙遜に平和の種を
まいて平和を刈り取ったのでしょうか
with Jehovah and with his people?
As you recall,
after Joshua led the Israelites
ヨシュアが率いるイスラエル人が
ヨルダン川を渡って約束の地に入った後
across the Jordan River
into the Promised Land,
Jehovah directed them to remove
エホバは彼らにカナンの国々を
滅ぼすようにと指示しました
the pagan Canaanite nations
who dwelled there.
This included the Gibeonites.
当然 ギベオンの人たちも
含まれていました
The account at Joshua chapter 9
ヨシュア 9章から分かるように
ギベオンの人たちは
informs us that the Gibeonites
were plainly told
カナン人を全て滅ぼすことが
エホバの意志であることを
that it was Jehovah’s will
that the Canaanites be annihilated.
はっきりと知らされていました
Israel’s stunning victories
over Jericho and Ai
イスラエルがエリコとアイを
打ち負かしたことからも
made it very clear that Jehovah
was fighting for his people,
エホバがイスラエル人のために
戦っていることは明らかでした
and the Gibeonites did not want to be next.
ギベオンの人たちは恐れました
But what could they do
if this was Jehovah’s will?
でも 滅びることがエホバの意志なら
何ができるでしょうか
Well, they devised an interesting plan.
ある名案を思い付きました
They sent representatives to seek peace
代表者たちを送って イスラエル人と
エホバと和平を結ぶことにしたのです
with the Israelites and thereby with Jehovah.
According to verse 11, they were instructed:
9:11にはこんな言葉があります
「私どもはあなた方に仕えます
“We will be your servants;
now make a covenant with us.”
どうか私どもと契約を結んでください」
So this is what they were
to say as representatives.
これが和平を求める言葉でした
4節には 彼らが「抜け目ない
行動を取った」とあります
Verse 4 says that the Gibeonites
“acted shrewdly”
by trying to trick the Israelites
ぼろぼろの服や持ち物で
イスラエル人たちを
だまそうとしたのです
with their worn-out clothing and provisions,
pretending that they had traveled
from a very distant land
実際には30キロほどの距離でしたが
非常に遠い土地から来たように
見せ掛けました
but were actually just 20 miles (30 km) away.
うまくいったでしょうか
Did their plan work?
Despite their deception,
yes, their plan was successful.
だますのは良くないことでしたが
計画通りにいきました
In fact, in verse 15,
15節にあるように
ヨシュアはギベオンの人たちと
Joshua made a covenant of peace
with the Gibeonites.
平和の契約を結びました
Evidently, this was in harmony
with Jehovah’s will
このことはエホバの意志に
沿っていたと言えます
and reflected their humility
そして ギベオンの人たちの謙遜さと
and desire to seek peace
with Him and his people.
平和を求める態度の表れでした
They demonstrated
their humility and submission
ギベオンの人たちは
与えられた指示に従うことによって
to Jehovah’s will
and his representative, Joshua,
エホバの意志やエホバの代表者である
by following whatever direction
they received.
ヨシュアに従う謙遜さを表しました
In fact, notice the direction at verse 27;
27節にはこう書かれています
it says: “Joshua made them gatherers of wood
「その日 ヨシュアは彼らを
民およびエホバの祭壇のために
and drawers of water for the assembly
and for Jehovah’s altar.”
まきを集める者 水をくむ者とした」
ギベオンの男性たちは
腕の立つ戦士だったと思われますが
Although the Gibeonite men
were likely skilled warriors,
they were happy and content
to do whatever work
清い崇拝をサポートするために
どんな仕事でも喜んで行いました
they were given to support pure worship.
Humbly following direction
謙遜に指示に従ったので
命が守られ 平和を味わいました
saved their lives and brought them peace.
How can we imitate the Gibeonites?
どうすればギベオンの人たちに
倣えるでしょうか
By bringing our lives into harmony
with Jehovah’s will.
エホバの意志に沿った生き方を
することによってです
For some, this may require
making big changes,
かなり大きな変化が
必要な場合もあります
考え方を変えたり 悪い習慣をやめたり
adjusting their thinking,
giving up harmful practices,
良くない交友を避けたりします
and avoiding bad associates.
We can also imitate the Gibeonites
by being willing
ほかにもギベオンの人たちに倣える点は
清い崇拝をサポートするために
to perform whatever assignments we are given
与えられるどんな割り当ても
喜んで果たすことです
to humbly support pure worship.
So the lesson is clear.
何が分かりましたか
平和を刈り取るには
Sowing and reaping peace
謙遜に指示に従う
必要がある ということです
requires humbly following direction.
This lesson is highlighted
in the following dramatization.
そのことが次のビデオの中で
強調されています
Notice the benefits of submitting
to Jehovah’s direction.
エホバの指示に従うなら
良い結果になります
You see,
そうだった
the pandemic lasted longer
than any of us expected,
パンデミックがあんなに長く続くとは
誰も思わなかった
and all the conflicting news reports
just added to the stress.
いろいろなニュースが飛び交って
何を信じていいか分からなかった
妹が失業してうちに引っ越してきた
Then my sister lost her job
and had to move in with us.
So, yeah, it was me
それで 私とケリー 妹 父の
4人で暮らすことになった
and Kelly, Nicole, and Dad.
20秒だぞ 手洗いは20秒
Twenty seconds, Son
—twenty seconds.
I’ll see you later.
行ってくんね
Yeah.
うん
Uh, where’s your mask?
あ マスクは？
Don’t worry.
要らない
Here, you can use this one.
これ これ使って
I won’t get near anyone.
ちゃんとディスタンス取るから
兄さん？
Gary.
Listen!
仕事場では誰も
マスクなんか着けてないんだ
Nobody at the warehouse is wearing masks.
会社で何人感染したか知ってる？
ゼロだよ
And do you know how many people
have actually gotten sick?
Zero.
So far.
今はまだね この間の
統治体からの話 見ただろ
You saw the last Governing Body update.
警戒を緩めちゃいけない 油断するな
We can’t let down our guard.
Not now.
Dad, I get it.
そんなの分かってるよ
OK?
Look, I think it’s great that the brothers
are trying to keep us safe.
そりゃ 僕たちを守ろうとしてくれてる
っていうのはうれしいけど でも・・・
But . . .
But what?
でも何？
Don’t you think that they’re,
you know, overreacting?
でも ちょっと兄弟たち
深刻に考え過ぎじゃない？
But, of course, it wasn’t
the brothers who had the problem.
でももちろん 統治体の兄弟たちは
間違っていなかった
It was me.
私が間違っていた
A week later, I found out that a friend
in our service group
1週間後 グループの若い兄弟が
was in the hospital with COVID-19.
コロナで入院した
He was young, and he had been taking
all the right precautions.
兄弟はしっかり感染対策をしていたのに
I had really let my guard down.
自分が油断していたことに気付いた
Now is not the time
今は警戒を緩めるべき時ではありません
to slacken our hand when it comes to safety.
油断することなく
用心し続けましょう
Don’t let your guard down.
Don’t think the virus
can’t affect you or your family.
「うちの家族は大丈夫」とは
考えないでください
エホバの組織が私たちを
本当に守ろうとしていたこと
I saw how the organization
was really trying to protect us
and how much my decisions
were affecting others,
自分の決定が他の人に
大きな影響を与えること
家族にも影響を与えることが分かった
including the people I love the most.
As the pandemic dragged on,
パンデミックが続く中
I learned the importance
of being humble and obedient.
謙遜に従うことがいかに大切かを学んだ
Following Jehovah’s direction
didn’t just help us stay safe,
エホバからの指示に従うことで
安全に暮らせるだけでなく
it brought us peace.
平和でいられる
What timely lessons,
タイムリーな内容でしたね
especially with all that we are facing today!
今の状況にぴったり
当てはまっていました
Like Gary, there are times
ビデオに出てきた兄弟のように
that we may need
to adjust our thinking on matters
私たちも自分の意見や好みを
重視するのではなく
and put aside our personal opinions
and preferences
エホバの指示に謙遜に従うために
so we can loyally
and humbly follow Jehovah’s direction
考え方を調整する必要が
あるかもしれません
or whatever direction we receive
from his representatives,
もちろん エホバを代表している
「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」の指示に
ついても同じことが言えます
“the faithful and discreet slave.”
大切なことを学べました
Gary learned an important lesson:
Humbly following direction
謙遜に指示に従うなら
doesn’t just help our family stay safe,
家族が安全に暮らすのに
役立つだけでなく
it brings us happiness and peace
幸福や平和を味わえます
—a vital lesson for us today.
ぜひ覚えておきたい点ですね
いつも謙遜に指示に従う上で
What can help us
to humbly follow direction now
どんなことが助けになるでしょうか
as well as in the future?
Note what the apostle Paul said
エフェソス 5:17で
at Ephesians 5:17;
使徒パウロがどんなことを
述べているかに注目しましょう
he says: “Stop being unreasonable,
「もう無分別なことをしてはなりません
“but keep perceiving
いつでも エホバが何を
望んでいるかを見極めましょう」
what the will of Jehovah is.”
The Bible clearly shows
God’s thinking on matters.
聖書を読むと エホバが
望んでいることが分かります
But what if it’s not so clear to us
でも エホバの考えが
はっきり分からない時や
or we struggle to fully grasp
how it applies to us personally
自分の状況にどう当てはめたら
いいかがよく分からない時は
or in a given situation?
どうしたらいいでしょうか
What did Paul advise?
パウロによれば「エホバが何を望んで
いるかを見極め」ることが大切です
He said: “Keep perceiving
what the will of Jehovah is.”
How can we do that?
何ができますか
貴重な宝石を見つけるために
Well, just as a miner keeps digging
deep below the surface of the ground
地面の下を深く掘っていく
必要があるように
to find precious gems,
聖書を表面的に読むだけで
満足してはなりません
we must look beyond the surface
of what we read in the Bible.
This requires that we keep digging deep,
聖書を深く掘り下げて調べるようにし
carefully searching for gems
in the form of Bible principles.
宝石のような聖書の原則を
見つける努力を払いましょう
そして 祈りながら自分に
どう当てはまるかを考えます
Then we must prayerfully meditate
on what we find.
Then Jehovah’s precious thoughts
そうすると エホバと同じような
考え方ができるようになっていきます
will become our thoughts.
Perceiving Jehovah’s thinking on matters
エホバの考えを見極めるようにすれば
will help us to avoid getting
into a battle of wills,
自分の考えに固執しなくなるはずです
so we can follow His direction
エホバの指示や統治体からの指示にも
or whatever direction we receive
from the Governing Body.
喜んで従おうという気持ちになります
ギベオンの人たちのように
平和の種をまき
Like the Gibeonites, may we be peacemakers
エホバやエホバの民と
平和な関係でいられるようにしましょう
by continuing to sow peace
with Jehovah and his people.
As we humbly make Jehovah’s will our will,
謙遜にエホバの意志に従うなら
平和を刈り取っていつまでも
幸せに暮らせるでしょう
we will joyfully reap abundant peace forever.
次に 教育委員会の援助者
ケニス･フローディン兄弟が
Brother Kenneth Flodin,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now consider
the next talk of this symposium,
「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Gideon.”
ギデオン」という話をします
これからギデオンの例について
考えたいと思います
The man Gideon is
the Bible example we will consider.
But what is the challenge
this talk intends to address?
この話ではどんな問題を
取り上げると思いますか
Are you ready for this?
次の点です
Differences between fellow Christians.
仲間のクリスチャンとの間の不和です
You might think: ‘No, how can that be?
不和などあるんでしょうか
‘Jesus said the identifying mark
of his disciples
イエスは 自分の弟子たちは愛によって
見分けられると言ったのではないですか
would be the “love among [themselves],”
not the differences.’
And that is true.
もちろんそうです
In our Christian brotherhood,
we feel the love.
クリスチャンにとって愛は
一番大切であり
Love is prominent.
私たちはその愛を感じます
It is dominant.
でも 私たちはいわば
不完全さに染まっています
But as individuals,
we are drenched in imperfection.
Differences will inevitably erupt.
そのせいで不和が
生じてしまうことがあるのです
ヤコブ 3:2は率直に
James 3:2 doesn’t mince any words.
「私たちは皆 何度も
過ちを犯します」と言っています
It says: “We all [all] stumble many times.”
Not constantly, not every day
毎日とかしょっちゅうではないとしても
何度も過ちを犯してしまうのです
—but it acknowledges
that we make mistakes many times.
A brother or sister
may say something to hurt us.
誰かを傷つけてしまうかもしれません
Or maybe we push their emotional button
with words,
感情を害するようなことを
言ってしまったり
逆に言われたりします
or they push ours.
Usually, it’s not intentional.
大抵はわざとではなく
単なる誤解だったりします
Often it’s a misunderstanding.
We or they say something in good faith.
悪気はなく 何気なく言った言葉が
One thinks it appropriate;
the other does not.
相手の気に障る場合もあります
Or possibly what we said or did
自分が言ったことやしたことに対して
was perceived in a way
that we could not even have imagined.
思いがけない反応が
返ってくる場合もあります
いずれにしても 不和が生じたなら
But it happened, and now we must
平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取らなければなりません
sow peace in order to reap peace.
And when we plant seeds,
種をまいてから実を刈り取るまで
あまりかからない場合もあります
some germinate much faster than others.
In the opening talk of this symposium,
このシンポジウムの
最初の話でも考えた通り
it acknowledged that a farmer trusts
農業をする人のように 実がなることを
確信して種をまきましょう
he will see results in due time.
仲間のクリスチャンとの間に
不和が生じた場合
If we find ourselves
at odds with a fellow Christian,
ギデオンの例について考えると
the Bible example of Gideon
can help us to sow and reap peace.
平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取るのに役立ちます
ギデオンは
ミディアン人と戦っていた時
Now, Gideon was at war with the Midianites,
and he asked his fellow worshippers,
the Ephraimites,
仲間であるエフライムの人たちに
追撃するよう頼みました
to help chase them down
「裁き人の書」にある通りです
—Judges chapter 8.
戦いは大勝利に終わりました
They had tremendous success.
We say, “Great.”
ところが エフライムの人たちは感情を
害して ギデオンに詰め寄りました
But after the battle,
the Ephraimites were offended.
They tried to pick a fight with Gideon.
They felt that Gideon
did not call them into battle soon enough.
もっと早く戦いに呼んでほしかった と
不満をぶつけたのです
裁き人 8:1
Judges 8:1:
「エフライムの人たちは
ギデオンに言った
“Then the men of Ephraim said to him:
‘What have you done to us?
『一体どういうつもりだ
ミディアンと戦う時に
“Why did you not call us when you went
to fight against Midian?’
なぜわれわれを呼ばなかったんだ』
そしてひどく文句を言った」
And they quarreled bitterly with him.”
Well, these are all armed, fighting men.
この人たちは武装した兵士でした
If this difference of opinion
was allowed to escalate,
もし不和が解決されなければ
大変なことになっていたかもしれません
it could get out of hand very quickly.
In fact, in this case,
もしかしたら殺し合いに発展していた
可能性もあります
hand-to-hand combat might have ensued.
Instead, though,
ではこの時 ギデオンは
どのように平和の種をまいたでしょうか
how did Gideon sow peace with words?
Let’s read verses 2 and 3:
2, 3節を読みましょう
「ギデオンは言った
『皆さんがしたことに比べれば
“He [Gideon] said to them:
“‘What have I done compared with you?
私は大したことはしていません
エフライムのブドウの収穫の残りは
“‘Are not the gleanings of Ephraim
better than the grape harvest of Abiezer?
アビ･エゼルの収穫に
勝っているではありませんか
“‘It was into your hand that God
gave Midian’s princes Oreb and Zeeb,
神はミディアンの高官オレブと
ゼエブを皆さんの手に渡しました
皆さんがしたことに比べれば
私は大したことはしていません』
“and what have I done compared with you?’
“[and notice]
［次です］ギデオンがこう話すと
When he spoke this way, they calmed down.”
エフライムの人たちの
気持ちは治まった」
Now, in this case,
the germination period was very short.
この時は 割とすぐに
平和を刈り取れました
Gideon sowed peace with well-chosen words,
ギデオンは よく考えた言葉で
平和の種をまき
and he reaped peace in one conversation.
1回の会話で
平和を刈り取ることができました
Now, in the following dramatization,
次のビデオの中で ある兄弟が
notice how a brother prevents the situation
誤解が深刻な不和に発展しないために
どうするかに注目しましょう
from escalating into a confrontation.
And you know how Jehovah’s people are.
エホバの証人ってすごいですよね
When there’s a need,
何かが起きると 兄弟たちは
すぐ助けに行きますよね
our brothers step up.
So even though we had
そういえば あの時も
仕事がたくさんあった・・・
a lot of work to do back then,
we always had willing workers
援助を申し出る人がいつもいた
でも 働きたい人が多かったので
—so many workers that some started to feel
like they were being overlooked.
自分が外されているんじゃないかと
思う人が出てきた
Hey, Ray!
What’s up?
あ レイ どうしたの？
Hey, Matt,
マシュー 君が会衆の食料分配を
担当してるんだって？
I hear you’re organizing
the food distribution for our congregation.
うん 何とかやってる
Yeah, I’m trying my best.
何か手伝える？
僕のトラック いつでも使えるよ
Yeah, well, can I give you a hand?
My truck is all ready to go.
We actually just finished loading up
for the day, so I think we’re good.
今日の荷物は全部
積み終わったから 大丈夫かも
でも声を掛けてくれてほんとありがとう
But, wow, yeah,
thank you very much for offering.
OK.
When’s the next run?
そう じゃあ 次配るのはいつ？
You know what, Ray?
実は これから出るところなんだ
後でかけ直してもいい？
We’re about to pull out right now.
Is it OK if I call you back?
Yeah.
Yeah, sure.
ああ うん 分かった
レイは本当によく働く兄弟で
Ray was such a hard worker,
more than most of us even realized.
僕たちの知らないところでも
よく動いていた
He put his heart into every assignment.
どんな奉仕も一生懸命やっていた
Who was that?
誰だったの？
But when I told him
「奉仕者は十分集まった」って伝えたら
we already had all the help we needed,
思ってもない反応が返ってきた
it didn’t go the way I hoped.
Ray, I think you’re muted.
レイ ミュートじゃない？
ということは 僕には奉仕に
参加する資格がないってこと？
So, what you’re saying is
you don’t think I’m qualified to help out.
いや そうじゃなくって
No, no, we just—
お母さんのお世話 一生懸命
してるでしょ だからレイには・・・
We know how hard
you’re working caring for your mom.
We didn’t want to . . .
ポールも今回入ってなかった？
Isn’t Paul Thompson on your crew?
うん そうだけど
Yeah, but—
あとオリバーは？
And Oliver Kagan?
オリバーは補佐を
やってくれているけど・・・
Oliver’s my assistant, yes, but—
So how does this work, Matt?
どうやって選んでいるの？マシュー
I mean, you just use your friends,
友達ばっかり選んで
ほかの人は入れないんだ
and you shut the rest of us out.
兄弟たちが僕のことを
無視しているとしか思えないんだけど
Don’t you think I notice
how you brothers ignore me?
Ray, I owe you an apology.
レイ
ほんと悪かった
I’m so sorry.
ごめんね
最初からきちんと話しておけばよかった
I should’ve spoken with you
about this right from the start.
レイはお母さんのお世話
一生懸命してるよね
You’re working so hard
taking care of your mom.
これ以上負担増やしたくないと思って
The last thing we wanted to do
was make things harder for you.
But even more than that,
それもあるんだけど
we didn’t want to have to ask you
to do something
レイとお母さんを
感染のリスクにさらすようなことを
that would put you
or your mother at higher risk.
お願いしたくなかったんだ
I know.
そうだね それは僕も心配してる
I worry about that too.
You know,
そうだよね 万一
your mom
—we wouldn’t want anything to happen to her.
お母さんに何かあったら大変だし
She’s one of our congregation treasures.
姉妹は会衆の宝だから
ありがとう
I know.
レイも大切だけどね
And you’re not so bad either.
いや ほんとに
レイはみんなの手本だよ
Seriously, you’re such a good example.
Think how Jehovah must feel when he sees
エホバはレイが会衆やお母さんのために
していることをよく見ている
all that you’re doing
for us and for your mom.
そして喜んでいるよ
Thank you.
ありがとう すごくうれしい
That means a lot to me.
If something comes up
that I can help with then
もし ちょっとでも
できることがあったら
—even just a little—
and I can do it from home—
リモートでもできることなら
喜んでやるよ
Well, that’s a good point.
あ それはいいね
Maybe I can get your thoughts
on something, if that’s OK?
じゃあ 早速何かお願いしようかな
いかがでしたか
Two good brothers
2人ともいい兄弟でしたが
—but because of imperfection,
they were both looking
不完全さのせいで同じ状況を
別々の観点から見ていました
at the exact same situation
from two different perspectives.
Matt was well-intended
in what he did for Ray.
マシューはレイのためを思って
仕事を頼みませんでした
He realized he was caring
レイの母親が病気だったので
配慮したのです
for his ailing mother;
he was trying to protect him.
でも レイは腹を立てました
But Ray was offended.
He even accused Matt of showing favoritism
マシューが友達ばかりを選んで自分を
無視している と言って責めました
to his friends and ignoring others.
では どう解決されましたか
Well, how did this calm down?
Well, first of all, thankfully,
まず 幸いなことに
レイとマシューは2人きりで話して
Ray went directly to Matt
and expressed his feelings
between the two of them alone.
レイは気持ちを伝えることができました
Well, how did that allow for a follow-up?
その結果どうなったでしょうか
マシューはレイの話をよく聞いて
Well, Matt now had the opportunity
to absorb and understand Ray’s concerns.
レイの気持ちを
理解することができました
What a blessing that was!
本当に良かったですね
それからどのように会話が
続いていきましたか
And so, what followed after that?
Well, you remember, when he grasped it,
マシューはレイの気持ちが分かった後
謝っていましたね
Matt paused and apologized.
His words—like Gideon’s, well-spoken—
ギデオンのようによく考えられた言葉を
言ってレイを落ち着かせ
calmed Ray down.
平和の種をまくことができました
It was a short germination period.
He sowed and reaped peace
in one conversation.
1回の会話で平和を刈り取れました
Well, how can we imitate Gideon
では 今後仲間との間に
不和が生じた場合
when there are future differences
with fellow worshippers?
どのようにギデオンに倣えるでしょうか
Second Timothy 2:24
テモテ第二に鍵があります
エフライムの人たちのことを
思い起こすと
—(And you recall that when the men of Ephraim
confronted Gideon, they were confrontational.
ギデオンに対してかなりけんか腰でした
They were upset;
they were rattling their sabers.)
剣を振りかざしているかのようでした
but here, Paul, in effect,
でもパウロの言葉に
ギデオンが示した態度が
よく言い表されています
summarizes for Christians Gideon’s demeanor.
Second Timothy 2:24:
テモテ第二 2:24
「主の奴隷は争う必要はありません
［言葉でも剣でもです］
“For a slave of the Lord
does not need to fight,
“[you see, with words or swords,
instead like Gideon, it says]
必要なのは ［ギデオンのように］
誰にでも穏やかに接すること
“but needs to be gentle toward all,
“qualified to teach, [and notice this]
［そして大事なのは ］不当な扱いを
受けても自分を抑えること」です
showing restraint when wronged.”
簡単ではありませんが 「不当な扱いを
受けても自分を抑える」なら
That is not easy to do.
But “showing restraint when wronged”
is a means of sowing peace.
平和の種をまくことができます
Now, if it’s just a minor offense,
we might ask ourselves,
相手に落ち度があっても
それがささいな問題なら
‘Can I put up with this slight
to avoid a confrontation?’
あえて取り上げないことに
できるかもしれません
でもマシューの場合
傷ついたレイに感情をぶつけられました
But, of course, in the case with Ray,
he felt deeply hurt.
Matt realized the perspective was different.
マシューは相手の観点が違うことに
気付きましたが
But you remember, in hindsight,
謙遜に「最初からきちんと
話しておけばよかった」と言いました
Matt admitted,
‘I should have talked to you first.’
そのようにして平和の種を
まくことができたのです
With those words, he planted seeds of peace.
Now, amazingly,
long before the first century,
さて ギデオンは
1世紀よりずっと昔の人でしたが
Gideon manifested
後にクリスチャンたちに与えられた
大切な教えに従っていたと言えます
what later became a Christian principle.
フィリピ 2:3にあるように
At Philippians 2:3, it says:
“With humility consider others
superior to you.”
「自分より他の人の方が
上だと考え」ました
Do you remember Gideon’s exact expression?
ギデオンは何と言っていたでしょうか
Twice he said:
2回も「私は大したことは
していません」と言いました
“What have I done compared [to] you?”
その謙遜な態度により
His humility calmed
エフライムの人たちの気持ちは
治まりました
the Ephraimites down instantly.
どう倣えますか
So, what can we do?
Well, we can apologize
for our contribution to the difference,
たとえ自分には落ち度がないように
思えたとしても
even if the apology is done
on the other person’s terms.
不和が生じてしまったことについて
謙遜に謝れます
We can pray for him.
相手のために祈ったり
誠実に褒めたり 親切にしたりできます
We can give a sincere compliment;
do something kind for the person.
And if we have a discussion,
may our words be gracious
そして 話し合う場合には
快い言葉を優しく語るようにしましょう
and the tone kindly.
クリスチャンの仲間との間に
不和が生じても
Now, it would be nice if all the differences
between Christians
素早く解決できるなら
素晴らしいことです
could have a short germination cycle.
でも その時の状況や
But because of circumstances, personalities,
個性の違いや 問題の性質によって
or the nature of the issue,
that’s not always possible.
うまくいかないこともあります
But may we each
それでも 私たちは
平和の種をまくために
be determined to do our part to sow peace
自分にできることを行いましょう
そして いずれ平和を刈り取れることを
確信して 待ちましょう
and, like the farmer,
expect peace in due time.
And, oh,
そうすれば
how sweet restored peace truly is!
素晴らしい平和の実を
存分に味わうことができるでしょう
出版委員会の援助者
ロバート･ルシオーニ兄弟が
And now, Brother Robert Luccioni,
a helper to the Publishing Committee,
このシンポジウムの次の話をします
will give the next talk
of this symposium, entitled
主題は 「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち アビガイル」
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Abigail.”
平和をつくるのは簡単ではありません
Pursuing peace can be a challenge.
私たちは不完全ですし
Because of our imperfections
and the complexities of life,
いろいろな問題に直面するので
we have to work for peace,
even under normal conditions.
普段でも平和をつくるには
努力が必要です
But pursuing peace
becomes a greater challenge
でも もっと大変なのは
1人で奮闘しなければならない場合です
when it’s one-sided.
家庭や会衆で 自分は
平和をつくりたいのに
Difficulties arise in the family
and in the congregation
相手にその気がない場合
難しく感じることでしょう
when one person pursues peace
but the other does not.
For example, in the congregation,
perhaps we have a friend
例えば 会衆内にいる自分の友達が
who has a problem with another friend
in the congregation
別の友達と仲たがいしているものの
but does not do anything
to reconcile the situation,
仲直りしようとしないかもしれません
or in the family, a Christian mate
あるいは 家庭内で配偶者が
聖書の教えに従おうとしないため
may have difficulty pursuing peace
if his or her spouse
does not apply Bible principles.
平和をつくるのが難しく
感じる場合があります
Well, what do we do then?
どうしたらいいでしょうか
Well, in those situations,
そういう場合に 聖書のアビガイルの
手本を参考にできるかもしれません
the Bible account of Abigail may be helpful.
I invite you to turn in your Bibles
to 1 Samuel chapter 25,
サムエル第一 25章を開いて
アビガイルと夫のナバルについて
書かれていることを考えてみましょう
and here we’re introduced to Abigail
and her husband, Nabal.
And you notice here in verse 3,
Nabal is described as “harsh.”
3節には ナバルが「荒っぽ［い］」
人だったと書かれています
25節では アビガイルが
ナバルのことを
In verse 25,
Abigail describes him as ‘senseless.’
「分別がない」と言っています
In verse 17, his own worker
17節では ナバルの召し使いが
「ご主人はどうしようもない方で
誰も何も言えない」と言っています
describes him as “worthless”
and says “no one can speak [with] him.”
こういう性格の人でしたから
Well, with a personality like that,
ダビデの部下たちにひどい態度を
取ったのもうなずけます
it’s not surprising
that he mistreats David’s young men.
And now David wants revenge.
ダビデは復讐心に燃えます
How do you pursue peace
in a situation like that?
こういう状況でどうすれば
平和をつくれるでしょうか
Well, what does Abigail do?
アビガイルはどうしましたか
Well, think about it.
考えてみると どうすることも
できたでしょうか
What she could have done.
See, Abigail could have done nothing.
何もしないという
選択肢もあったでしょう
It’s not hard to imagine that she had
ナバルと一緒に暮らすのは
大変だったに違いありません
a difficult life as well
living with this man.
それで ただ黙ってダビデの行動を
見守ることもできたでしょう
She could have just stepped back
and let David come through
and do what he had in mind.
あるいは ダビデに会いに行って
火に油を注ぐこともできました
Or she could have gone out to David
and inflamed the situation,
ナバルのせいで自分も
ひどい目に遭ってきた と
maybe describing what a terrible man he is
and how he mistreats her as well.
話すこともできたでしょう
See, either of these approaches
そのようにしていたら自分にとって
楽だったかもしれませんが
could have made her life easier,
but she didn’t do that.
そうしませんでした
Now, Abigail could not change
her husband’s ways,
アビガイルは 夫の行動を
変えることはできませんでしたが
but she did what she could
to defuse an escalating conflict.
悲惨な争いに発展しないように
自分にできることをしました
サムエル第一 25章に戻って
In fact, notice her respectful,
well-chosen words.
アビガイルの言葉に注目してみましょう
Let’s go back to 1 Samuel 25,
27-31節を読みたいと思います
and let’s read verses 27-31:
「あなたのために持ってまいりました
この贈り物を
“Now let this gift that your servant girl
has brought to my lord
あなたに従う部下たちに
お与えください
“be given to the young men
who are following my lord.
“Pardon, please, the transgression
of your servant girl,
どうか私の違反をお許しください
“for Jehovah will without fail make
for my lord a lasting house,
あなたはエホバの戦いを
戦っておられるのですから
エホバは必ずあなたの家系を
存続させてくださいます
“because my lord
is fighting the wars of Jehovah,
あなたはこれまでずっと何の
悪いこともしてこられませんでした
“and no evil has been found
in you all your days.
“When someone rises up to pursue you
and seeks your life,
誰かがあなたを追跡して命を狙う時
あなたの命はエホバ神の命の袋の中に
安全に包まれます
“the life of my lord will be wrapped securely
“in the bag of life with Jehovah your God,
一方 神はあなたの敵の命を
“but the lives of your enemies
石投げ器で投げる石のように
放り投げます
“he will hurl away like stones from a sling.
エホバが約束通りあなたに
さまざまな良いことをしてくださり
“And when Jehovah has done for my lord
all the good things he has promised
“and he appoints you as leader over Israel,
あなたをイスラエルの
指導者に任命する時
“you will have no remorse
or regret in your heart
あなたは 理由もなく人の血を流して
“for shedding blood without cause
自分の手で復讐したという後悔の
気持ちを抱くことはありません
“and for letting the hand
of my lord take revenge.
“When Jehovah confers good upon my lord,
エホバがあなたに良くしてくださる時
どうか私を思い出してください」
remember your servant girl.”
Do you notice what Abigail does?
アビガイルはどうしたでしょうか
She comes in with a gift,
贈り物を持ってきて
ダビデの前でひれ伏し
she bows down to David,
she takes the blame
for the situation herself,
「悪いのはこの私です」と言ってから
神の考えに沿ったことを話して
ダビデに訴え掛けました
and she reasons with him
using godly principles.
Abigail’s actions calm David
アビガイルはダビデの気持ちを静め
災難を回避できました
and avert a calamity.
She pursued peace.
まさに平和をつくったのです
But to do that, she had to look
beyond her own feelings
アビガイルは自分のことよりも
エホバのお名前のために
どう行動するのが最善かを考えました
and consider what was best
for Jehovah’s name.
それは簡単ではありません
And that is not always easy to do.
But what was the result?
でもどうなりましたか
Because she sowed peace—she pursued peace—
平和の種をまいたので
平和を刈り取ることができました
she reaped peace.
How can we benefit from Abigail’s example?
この手本にどのように倣えるでしょうか
Why is it important to do so now?
倣うことはなぜ大切でしょうか
Let’s look at the following dramatization.
次のビデオを見て 考えてみましょう
And later on,
その後 状況が難しくなって
when things got even more intense,
that’s when our peace
was really put to the test.
平和に仲良くやっていくことが
試されたんですよ
でも ティムは みんなが前向きで
いられるよう助けてくれましたね
Yeah, but, Tim, you always
found a way to keep us positive.
その点は エイミーから
いろいろ学びました
Well, I learned a lot about that
from my better half.
Amy has always had a way
of bringing people together.
みんなが仲良くなれるよう
よく助けていたんです
For example, just before the pandemic,
例えば コロナが始まる前
there were these two pioneer sisters
in our congregation.
2人の開拓者の間で
ちょっとしたことがあったんです
Becky was energetic, industrious,
and fearless in her ministry,
ベッキーは 元気によく働き
物おじせずに伝道する人
and Lena was experienced, self-sacrificing,
レナは経験もあり 人のためによく動き
and such a good Bible teacher.
教えるのが上手だった
お互い受け入れられないところが
あったみたいです
But they didn’t exactly get along.
Are you ready to go?
もう行ける？
Are you OK?
大丈夫？
It’s just— It’s Becky.
はあ ベッキーったら 本当に
形だけの開拓者なんだから
She’s just such a phantom pioneer.
We never see her.
全然奉仕に出てこない
I’m sorry, but she just needs
to be more serious
こんなこと言っちゃいけないけど
もっとちゃんと奉仕した方がいいと思う
about her ministry.
ベッキー 大都市の
公共エリアやってるし・・・
Well, she’s been doing
metro witnessing and . . .
うんうん知ってる で LDCもでしょ
I know, I know, and LDC too, right?
She does plumbing?
確か 設備だっけ？
Concrete.
基礎工事 ベッキー体力あるからね
She does have a lot of energy!
私たちも前はそうだったよね
Do you remember
when we used to be like that?
I don’t know that I was ever like Becky.
ベッキーほどじゃないと思うけどね
No, you weren’t.
そんなことない 今のベッキー
なんてもんじゃなかったじゃない
You were Beckyer than Becky.
I couldn’t keep up with you
レナのペースに付いていけなかった
あの赤い車で一日中奉仕したよね
—those long service days
in your little red car.
That feels like a long time ago.
すごい前のことに感じる
Yeah.
そうね
あのね ベッキー見てると
レナみたいって思う
You know, Becky reminds me a lot of you
—I mean both of us—
ていうか 私たち 20年前の
twenty years ago.
She’s working so hard,
ベッキーはよく働くし
and she’s made
so many sacrifices
エホバへの奉仕を一生懸命やってる
for the truth,
just like you have.
レナみたいにね
I think we should get together
今度一緒にお茶しない？
ベッキーも呼んで
—the three of us.
もっと知り合えるかもよ
You should get to know her better.
The next week,
I had them both over to the house.
次の週 2人を家に呼んだんです
And the more those two
got to know each other,
2人とも お互いのことを
よく知るにつれて
the closer they became.
仲良くなれたんですよ
You know that proverb:
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”?
「賢い人たちの舌は
人を癒やす」という格言
Amy taught me what that verse really means.
エイミーはその言葉を実践していました
OK, everyone out!
よし みんな集合！
When everything changed
急に状況が変わって
and we suddenly
found ourselves locked up together,
同じ刑務所に入れられた時
I tried to show that same spirit
みんなが一致するために
いつも平和を心掛けた
so that we could stay united.
And with Jehovah’s help,
エホバの助けで
we did.
そうできた
Now, did you notice what our sister did
and did not do?
エイミーにはどんな選択肢が
あったと思いますか
She could have done nothing.
何もせず レナがベッキーに対して
She could have let Lena, her service partner,
ネガティブな感情を抱くままに
することもできたかもしれません
cultivate those thoughts about Becky.
あるいは レナに同意したり
Or Amy could have poured fuel
on the situation,
自分もベッキーに
いら立っていると言ったりして
maybe agreeing with Lena
or telling a few stories
火に油を注ぐことも
できたかもしれません
about how Becky annoyed her as well.
でもそうしませんでした
But she did not do that.
See, Amy’s desire to sow peace
moved her to help Lena
レナがベッキーのことを違う観点で
見ることができるように助けて
see things from a different perspective.
平和の種をまいたのです
And as a result, the congregation benefited
その結果 2人は仲良くなり
平和を刈り取ることができました
and reaped peace.
Notice how the apostle Paul explains
私たちも ぜひエイミーと同じような
行動を取りたいと思います
this approach that we should take
if you turn in your Bibles
その点で使徒パウロが何と
言っているかに注目してみましょう
to Romans 12:18
—Romans 12:18:
ローマ 12:18です
“If possible, as far as it depends on you,
「できる限りのことをして
どんな人とも平和な関係で
いるようにしましょう」
be peaceable with all men.”
「できる限りのことをして」とあります
“As far as it depends on you”
—see, our congregations
and our families benefit
問題が深刻になる前に
できる限り平和の種をまくなら
when we sow seeds of peace
会衆や家庭の平和に貢献できます
before matters get out of hand.
例えば 家の中で何かが
燃えていたらどうしますか
It’s like seeing a small fire in our house.
What do we do?
そのうち消えると考えて無視しますか
油を掛けますか
Do we just ignore it—hope it goes away?
Do we fan the flames?
Do we put fuel on it?
いえ もちろんすぐに
消そうとしますよね
No, we do something.
Why?
そうしなければ自分の家が
大変なことになってしまうと
Because we know that if left unchecked,
that fire could destroy our home.
分かっているからです
Well, it’s similar when we see problems
that develop
平和を乱すような問題が起きたときにも
同じことが当てはまります
and peace being disrupted.
何もせずに問題を放置したり
We do the same.
Why?
Because we know that if we don’t
do something and if it’s left unchecked,
悪化させたりするなら
どうなるでしょうか
that disturbance could destroy our family
その問題のせいで 家庭や会衆が
大変なことになってしまうでしょう
and the congregation.
では どうすれば平和の種を
まくことができるでしょうか
So the question is,
How do we sow seeds of peace?
Well, Abigail was a good example.
アビガイルの手本を
思い起こしてみましょう
Did you notice what she did?
She considered how best
to approach the situation.
アビガイルは どうするのが最善かを
よく考えて 行動しました
She was proactive.
問題を放置したりしませんでした
She didn’t just hope
it would go away on its own.
She used respectful, soothing speech.
敬意を込めて ダビデの
気持ちを静めました
She was careful not to fan the flames
or add fuel to it
火に油を注ぐようなことに
ならないように注意しました
—all good steps we can take.
そうした点に倣いましょう
And we have other resources
to help us as well.
ほかにもどんなことができるでしょうか
聖書やエホバの証人の
出版物を調べるなら
We can do research in the Bible
and in our publications
どうすれば平和の種を
まけるかがさらに分かります
to see how others have sowed peace
in similar situations,
長老にアドバイスを
求めることもできます
and we can also consult with the elders.
平和をつくるのが特に大変なのは
どんな場合でしょうか
Now, we understand that this
is especially a challenge
if the situation is in the family,
as it was for Abigail.
アビガイルのように 家庭内の
平和が乱されている場合です
とてもつらいですね
That is not easy at all.
そういう状況でも
And in those situations,
配偶者の良いところに目を
向けるようにしましょう
try to focus on your mate’s good qualities,
not on his or her irritating traits.
気に入らないところばかり
見ないようにします
さて 現実的な見方も必要です
But with all of this,
we have to be realistic.
Remember what the apostle Paul said there
as recorded in verse 18.
使徒パウロが何と言っていたか
覚えていますか
He said “if possible,
ローマ 12:18で
「できる限りのことをして」
と言っていました
as far as it depends on you.”
「できる限りのことをして」も
So Paul is acknowledging
that peace with others
平和をつくれない場合もある
ということです
may not always be possible.
So, what do we do?
そういう場合 自分の
ベストを尽くしたら
We have to do the best that we can,
後はエホバに委ねるようにしましょう
and then we leave the rest
in Jehovah’s hands.
So may we be determined
では 平和をつくることを
いつも意識するようにして
to develop the practice
of pursuing peace now.
努力を続けていきましょう
Whether we’re in the congregation
or in the family,
会衆内でも家庭内でも
私たちが平和の種をまく努力をするなら
we can be confident that if we sow peace,
きっと平和を刈り取れるでしょう
we will reap peace,
even if others don’t respond.
たとえ相手がなかなか応じなくてもです
How?
エホバとの平和と心の平和を味わい
Well, we’ll have peace with Jehovah,
peace with ourselves,
and the knowledge
that we did the right thing.
満たされた気持ちになるからです
Additionally, when in the future
それでは 今後いろいろな
問題が生じたとしても
a force for peace is vitally needed,
ぜひアビガイルのように
we will be prepared to provide it.
平和をつくる人になりましょう
次に 教育委員会の援助者
ウィリアム・マレンフォント兄弟が
Brother William Malenfant,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
will now consider
the next talk of this symposium,
「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Mephibosheth.”
メピボセテ」という話をします
私たちは不完全です
Inherited imperfection
—we don’t like it, but we all have it.
残念ですが それが現実です
And since imperfection means
不完全ですから 誰でも間違いを
してしまうことがあります
that everyone is less than perfect,
we are bound to be treated unfairly at times,
それで 不公平な扱いを
受けることもあります
even by fellow Christians.
仲間のクリスチャンからもです
In rare cases, one might become
the victim of slander
めったにないことですが
中傷や詐欺の被害に遭うことさえ
あるかもしれません
or even fraud.
Consider with me an account about slander
聖書に出てくる中傷の例を考えましょう
それはダビデ王の時代に
イスラエルで起きたことです
that occurred in the nation of Israel
in the days of King David.
It’s about a man named Mephibosheth
メピボセテという名の人が
who was slandered by a man named Ziba.
ツィバという名の人から
中傷を受けました
Examining the way
その時にメピボセテがどう行動したかに
注目したいと思います
that Mephibosheth handled this matter
can be of real help to us to sow peace
そうすると 私たちが平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取るのに役立ちます
and to reap peace.
Jonathan was Mephibosheth’s father,
メピボセテの父親は
ダビデの親友ヨナタンで
and King Saul was his grandfather.
祖父はサウル王でした
When Jonathan and Saul died,
ヨナタンとサウルが死んだ時
King David gave to Mephibosheth
ダビデ王は残されたメピボセテに
祖父の土地を全て与えました
all the land of his grandfather.
そしてツィバを
メピボセテの召し使いにし
David assigned Ziba as a servant
メピボセテに与えた土地を
管理させることにしました
to take care of the land
that he had given to Mephibosheth.
しばらくして ダビデの息子が
謀反を起こしたため
Sometime later, a rebellion
in David’s household
ダビデはエルサレムから逃げました
forced him to flee from Jerusalem,
and Ziba went out to meet David.
その時ツィバがダビデに会いに行きます
When David asked Ziba about Mephibosheth
ダビデがツィバに
どうしてメピボセテは
一緒に来なかったのかと尋ねると
and why he didn’t come with Ziba
ツィバはメピボセテを中傷しました
to show his support for David,
Ziba slandered Mephibosheth,
全く事実ではありませんでしたが
「メピボセテは自分が王になることを
望んでいる」と言ったのです
saying that he was seeking the kingship
for himself.
残念なことに
Sad to say, David believed the slander
ダビデはツィバのうそをうのみにし
and gave Mephibosheth’s land to Ziba.
メピボセテの土地を
ツィバに与えてしまいました
しばらく後に メピボセテは
ダビデ王に会って
Sometime later, Mephibosheth
met with King David
and explained why he didn’t show up
自分がダビデと一緒に行かなかった
理由について説明します
to travel with him.
He told David that Ziba had lied about him.
そして ツィバがうそを
ついたことを伝えます
Upon hearing
Mephibosheth’s side of the story,
ダビデはメピボセテの話を聞いたものの
David now decided
土地を元には戻さず
that he and Ziba should share the land.
「ツィバと分け合いなさい」と言います
Instead of complaining or seeking vengeance,
でもメピボセテは 不平を言ったり
復讐心に燃えたりせず
Mephibosheth displayed
自分が平和をつくりたいと
思っていることを示しました
the spiritual qualities of a peacemaker,
不当な扱いを甘んじて受け入れたのです
and he was willing to be wronged.
He said to David, as recorded
メピボセテがダビデに何と言ったか
at 2 Samuel chapter 19
サムエル第二 19章を見てみましょう
and verse 30,
19章の30節です
these words:
“At this Mephibosheth said to the king:
「メピボセテは王に言った
“‘Let him take it all,
『王が無事に家に戻られたのですから
“‘now that my lord the king
全部彼のものになっても構いません』」
has come to his house in peace.’”
Yes, Mephibosheth was more concerned
そうです メピボセテにとって
ダビデ王が無事に戻ってきたことの方が
about David’s kingship
than he was about himself.
自分のことより大事でした
In the following dramatization,
これから流れるビデオの中で
notice how a brother reacts
ある兄弟が不当に思える処置に
どう反応するかを見ましょう
to a perceived injustice
そしてその後 どのように平和の種を
まくかに注目しましょう
and thereafter
how he sows peace with his brothers.
The first time we met David,
僕たちは刑務所の中で
デービッドに会ったんだよね
we were in chains!
I’d seen a lot of things
during my time as a guard,
看守だった時に
いろんな人を見てきましたけど
こんな平和な人たちを見たのは
初めてでした
but nothing like the peace that you all had.
Prison chains may be strong,
牢屋に閉じ込められても
but we all had something much stronger.
エホバからの平和はいつもありますよね
平和をつくるために努力したよね
But we had to work for that peace.
Right, Phil?
フィル
そうでしたね
That’s right.
実は ちょっとした誤解があって
See, there was a misunderstanding
that got blown all out of proportion.
それが大きな問題になっちゃったんです
私の対応も良くなかった
And I didn’t handle it the best.
自分の意見を言えば言うほど
The more I tried to defend myself,
the worse it became.
状況が悪くなっていった
これは何かの間違いだと思います
Brothers, there must be some mistake.
私がこんなことするはず
ないじゃないですか
This isn’t true.
You know me!
まさかこんなことになるとは
思わなかった
I wasn’t prepared
for how far it would go.
もう1つお知らせがあります
There’s one more announcement.
フィリップ・キム兄弟は
長老として奉仕しておられません
Brother Philip Kim
is no longer serving as an elder.
これで今日の集会は終わります
できる方は起立して⋯⋯
Well, that brings our meeting to a close.
Now we can stand.
その後の数カ月は本当に苦しかった
The next few months were a real struggle.
そのうち詳しい事情が明らかになり
But when more details came to light,
また長老になれると思った
I thought I’d be reappointed,
でもなれなかった
but I wasn’t.
Phil!
フィル！
なぜなのか分からなかった
I couldn’t understand why.
Phil, come on . . .
フィル ちょっと待って
I felt bitterness growing inside.
怒りが
頼むから
込み上げてきた
Phil, you know . . .
フィル ちょっとだけ・・・
Everything became about me
自分のことしか考えられなかった
—how I felt, what I deserved.
こんなことが許されるのか と思った
It was like a fog that stopped me
from seeing what Jehovah deserved,
頭が真っ白になって
エホバのことが
見えなくなっていたんです
エホバの助けが本当に必要でした
and I really needed his help.
I found comfort
in accounts of Jehovah’s servants
誤解されてもエホバに忠実に仕え続けた
聖書中の人たちの例を調べた
who were either misunderstood or misjudged
それを読んで考えさせられた
but maintained their loyalty to Him.
エホバの組織にいられるだけで
They helped me realize that it’s a privilege
幸せなことなんだと気付かされた
just to be in Jehovah’s organization.
兄弟たちとの平和は
Being at peace with my brothers
どんな立場で奉仕するか
ということより重要なんです
was more important
than any appointed position.
平和がなかったら その後の変化に
対応できたかどうか分からない
Without peace, I don’t know
how we could’ve managed what was to come.
関節 痛むんですね
Is your arthritis bad today?
Then I’ll be your secretary
私が書きますよ
just like Baruch was to Jeremiah.
エレミヤの秘書官バルクみたいに
フィルがいてくれてほんと助かるよ
I don’t know what I’d do without you.
では 私たち皆が考えたいのは
The question now for all of us is,
How can we imitate the example
どうすればメピボセテの模範に
倣えるかということです
of Mephibosheth?
First of all, if you are the victim
例えば 何かささいな
うわさを立てられたり
of minor gossip or rude treatment by someone,
失礼なことをされたりしたら
どうしますか
why not choose to let it pass
事を荒立てるのではなく
気にしないようにできるかもしれません
and not make a big issue of it?
Isn’t that what 1 Peter 4:8 advises?
ペテロ第一 4:8に従えます
First Peter 4:8 reads:
その聖句にはこうあります
“Above all things,
「何よりも 熱烈に
愛し合ってください」
have intense love for one another.”
And then it tells us what our love can do.
そして 愛するとどうなるかも
述べられています
It says:
“Because love covers a multitude of sins.”
「愛は多くの罪を覆うからです」
とあります
Yes, love covers sins and imperfections
そうです 私たちが進んで愛を表すなら
相手の罪や不完全さを
許すことができます
if we are willing
to let love have its way.
But what if you are the victim
では もっと深刻な状況に置かれた
場合にはどうしたらいいでしょうか
of a more serious injustice?
For example, the brother in the video
例えば ビデオの中の兄弟は
felt that he was a victim of injustice
長老の資格を失った時
自分は不当な扱いを
受けていると感じました
when he was deleted as an elder.
He tried to clarify matters,
疑いを晴らそうとしましたが
but since he didn’t get the response
he was hoping for,
長老たちから思うような反応が
返ってきませんでした
he became very upset.
それで感情を害しました
心の平和を失い
He lost his peace, and he caused others
結果として他の人たちとの
平和な関係も損なわれてしまいました
to lose their peaceful relationship with him.
To regain his peace,
兄弟は平和を取り戻すため
聖書をじっくり調べることにし
the brother dug into the Scriptures,
looking for examples he could benefit from.
自分にとって参考になる例を探しました
And he prayerfully looked to Jehovah
to help him.
そしてエホバに祈って助けを求めました
自制することや
He could see the importance of self-control
神の聖なる力に導かれることの
大切さを思い起こしました
and being guided by God’s spirit.
As a result, he was able
to be at peace with himself
その結果 心の平和を
取り戻すことができ
and sow peace with his brothers.
平和の種をまくことができました
Now, think for a moment
about the unfair decision David made
ダビデが下した不公平な
決定について思い返してみましょう
when he told Mephibosheth
メピボセテに対して
that he and Ziba were to share the land.
「ツィバと土地を分け合いなさい」
と言いました
Ziba was the cause of the problem,
not Mephibosheth.
悪いのはツィバで メピボセテは
何もしていないのにです
However, Mephibosheth
それでもメピボセテは 神の聖なる力に
導かれている人にふさわしい態度を示し
displayed the qualities of a spiritual man
by not looking out for his own interests,
自分の権利に固執しませんでした
よく辛抱し
by being patient,
and by not seeking vengeance.
復讐心を抱いたりしませんでした
Read with me
ご一緒にサムエル第二 19章を
読んでみましょう
at 2 Samuel chapter 19,
verse 25 through verse 28
25節から28節です
サムエル第二 19:25-28
—2 Samuel 19:25-28; it reads:
“When he came to Jerusalem
「彼［つまり メピボセテ］が
“[that is, Mephibosheth went to Jerusalem]
王を迎えるためにエルサレムに来た時
王は彼にこう言った
“to meet the king,
『メピボセテ あなたはどうして
私と一緒に来なかったのですか』
“the king said to him: ‘Why did you not go
with me, Mephibosheth?’
メピボセテは言った
“To this he said:
『ご主人さま 王よ 私は召し使いの
たくらみにはまったのです
“‘My lord the king, my servant tricked me.
“‘For your servant had said,
私は足が不自由ですので
“‘“Let me get my donkey saddled
“‘so that I may ride on it
and go with the king,”
「ロバに乗って王と一緒に行けるよう
くらを置いておいてください」
と言ってありました
“‘for your servant is crippled.
“‘But he slandered your servant
to my lord the king.
それなのに 彼は王の前で
私のことを中傷しました
“‘However, my lord the king
is like an angel of the true God,
ですが 王は真の神の
天使のような方ですから
王が良いと思うことをなさってください
“‘so do whatever seems good to you.
“‘All the household of my father
私の父の家の者は皆
“‘could have been doomed to death
by my lord the king,
王に滅ぼされてもおかしくないのに
“‘and yet you placed your servant
among those eating at your table.
あなたは私を同じ食卓に
着かせてくださいました
“‘So what right do I have
私には これ以上何かを王に
求める権利などございません』」
to cry out further to the king?’”
素晴らしいですね
It’s truly remarkable.
メピボセテはあるもので
満足していました
Mephibosheth was grateful for what he had,
and he was seeking nothing more.
ほかに何も求めませんでした
He enjoyed peace of mind and heart.
それで心の平和を感じていたのです
If a matter involving slander
私たちは 中傷や詐欺の被害を
受けたらどうすることができますか
or fraud arises today,
a Christian may choose to follow
Jesus’ instructions
マタイ 18:15-17のイエスの
指示に従うことにするかもしれません
at Matthew 18:15-17.
However, if for some reason,
では その通りに行動したのに問題が
解決されない場合はどうしますか
following that procedure
does not fully resolve the matter,
he or she may choose to pursue it no further
もうその件について それ以上
追求しないことにするかもしれません
and suffer a loss
その方が 会衆の平和を乱すより
良い場合があります
rather than disturb the peace
of the congregation.
We can leave any unresolved issues
with Jehovah,
解決されない問題は
エホバに委ねることができます
knowing that he sees what we do
エホバは 私たちの行動も
他の人の行動も見ています
and what others do,
and he will carry out justice
at the right time.
いずれ物事が正されるように
してくださることでしょう
For our own benefit,
私たちは憤りの気持ちを捨てるように
努力する必要があります
we really must try to let go of resentment.
When we do, we benefit ourselves.
そうすることは私たちのためになります
人を許すなら エホバも私たちのことを
許してくださいます
When we forgive, we forgive others
and Jehovah forgives us.
Now, that doesn’t mean
that we minimize or excuse
これは決して 仲間の重大な過ちを
見過ごすということではありません
the wrong conduct of fellow believers.
No.
でも ぜひメピボセテに倣って
But it does mean that we imitate Mephibosheth
by letting go of resentment
憤りの気持ちを捨て
平和を追い求めたいと思います
and pursuing peace.
We draw closer to Jehovah
エホバから離れないように
詩編 55:22の
アドバイスに従いましょう
by following the advice at Psalm 55:22:
“Throw your burden on Jehovah,
「重荷をエホバに委ねよ
そうすれば支えてくださる
“and he will sustain you.
神は正しい人が倒れることを
決して許さない」
Never will he allow
the righteous one to fall.”
And as Romans 15:13 assures us,
ローマ 15:13に
保証されている通り
Jehovah will “fill you with all joy and peace
エホバが「信仰を持つ皆さんを
あらゆる喜びと平和で
満たして」くださいますように
by your trusting in him.”
Brother Joel Dellinger,
a helper to the Service Committee,
奉仕委員会の援助者
ジョエル・デリンガー兄弟が
will now consider
the next talk of this symposium,
このシンポジウムの
次の話をしてくださいます
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
主題は 「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち
—Paul and Barnabas.”
パウロとバルナバ」
What’s the next challenge we’ll discuss?
次に考える問題は何でしょうか
It’s a disagreement between elders.
長老同士の口論や仲たがいです
長老の皆さん 経験がありますか
If you’re an elder,
have you experienced that?
Were voices raised?
ついかっとなってしまって
強い口調で話したり
Did tempers flare?
関係が悪くなってしまったり
したことがあるでしょうか
Has a friendship
with a fellow elder cooled off?
長老たちは模範的であることが
期待されていますが
Though we rightly expect
appointed brothers to be exemplary,
長老たちを含め 私たち皆は
不完全だというのが現実です
the fact is that all of us, including elders,
are still imperfect.
Differences in backgrounds,
personalities, experiences, and opinions
生い立ちや性格や考え方などが違うので
誰かとぶつかってしまうことがあります
can lead to disagreements.
その状況を放っておくなら 平和が
乱されてしまうことになりかねません
And a disagreement, if not resolved,
can disrupt our peace and that of others.
この話では 1世紀に
パウロとバルナバが
In this talk, we’ll consider
how two elders in the first century,
どのように平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取ったかを考えます
Paul and Barnabas, sowed and reaped peace.
2人の例から 現代の長老たちが
仲たがいを解決するのに役立つ事柄を
Let’s see how their example
can help appointed men today,
including all of you dear elders,
to resolve a disagreement.
ぜひ学ぶことにいたしましょう
ご一緒に使徒 15章を開いて
36節から39節を読んでみましょう
Please open your Bible with me
to Acts chapter 15
and read together verses 36 to 39.
パウロとバルナバの間にどんな問題が
生じたかに注目してください
In the reading, please note the problem
that arose between Paul and Barnabas.
That’s Acts chapter 15,
beginning in verse 36:
使徒 15章の36節からです
「何日か後 パウロはバルナバに言った
“After some days, Paul said to Barnabas:
“‘Let us now return and visit the brothers
in every one of the cities
『さあ エホバの言葉を広めた
全ての町に戻って兄弟たちを訪ね
“where we proclaimed the word of Jehovah,
to see how they are.’
どうしているかを見てみましょう』
バルナバは マルコと呼ばれるヨハネを
連れていくことに決めていた
“Barnabas was determined
to take along John, who was called Mark.
“Paul, however, was not in favor
of taking him along with them,
しかしパウロは パンフリアで
マルコが一緒に行動するのを
やめてしまったことがあるので
“seeing that he had departed
from them in Pamphylia
彼を連れていくことに賛成できなかった
“and had not gone with them to the work.
そこで怒りが激しくぶつかって
“At this there was a sharp burst of anger,
2人は別れることになった
“so that they separated from each other;
and Barnabas took Mark along
and sailed away to Cyprus.”
バルナバはマルコを連れて
船でキプロスに向かった」
問題は何でしたか
What was the problem?
These two elders strongly disagreed
パウロとバルナバは 宣教旅行に
マルコを連れていくかどうかについて
about whether to take Mark with them
on their next missionary tour.
意見が合いませんでした
もちろん 違う意見を言うこと自体は
間違ってはいません
Of course, expressing
a difference of opinion is not always wrong.
Verse 7 of this same chapter
reports that the apostles
15:7によると
エルサレムの使徒や長老たちは
「活発な論議」を行い
and older men in Jerusalem
had an “intense discussion”
それが良い結果につながりました
that led to a good outcome.
でもパウロたちはどうなりましたか
But in this case, what resulted?
Please look again at verse 39.
39節を見ましょう
ここに「パウロとバルナバは
It would be nice to read,
エホバに祈って合意に達した」と
書かれていたらよかったですね
“At this Paul and Barnabas prayed to Jehovah
and came to an agreement.”
でも残念なことに
この時の話し合いでは
Sadly, though,
their discussion on this occasion
パウロとバルナバの
「怒りが激しくぶつかって
led to a “sharp burst of anger,
2人は別れることに」なりました
so that they separated.”
As a result, their friendship
was affected by a temporary strain.
2人の友情に一時的に
ひびが入ってしまったようです
でも それは一時的でした
Why do we say “temporary”?
Because in time,
it appears that Paul and Barnabas
しばらくして パウロとバルナバは
仲直りすることができたようだからです
put this matter behind them.
少し後に パウロは「ガラテアの
クリスチャンへの手紙」の中で
A short time later
in Paul’s letter to the Galatians,
he wrote about Barnabas
and the activity they had enjoyed together.
バルナバや一緒にした活動に
ついて書いています
And Paul did not bring up their dispute.
争ったことについては触れていません
さらに コロサイのクリスチャンや
テモテに書いた手紙の中で
Also, when Paul later wrote
to the Colossians and then to Timothy,
パウロはマルコのことを褒めています
Paul spoke well of Mark.
最後に書いた「テモテへの第二の
手紙」の中では こう言っています
In fact, in Paul’s last inspired letter,
the second to Timothy, he wrote this:
「マルコを連れてきてください
私の奉仕を支えてくれるからです」
“Bring Mark along with you,
for he is helpful to me in the ministry.”
ですから パウロとバルナバは
Yes, it seems that Paul and Barnabas
仲たがいを解決することが
できたようです
resolved their disagreement.
Now, let’s think about that, brothers.
では考えてみましょう
What made that possible?
どうしてそうできたのでしょうか
これが理由です
It’s this: Long before their disagreement,
仲たがいをするずっと前から
2人は一緒に熱心に宣教をしていました
they had shared together
in an exciting ministry.
For years, they were united
何年もの間 聖書が言う
「平和という絆」で
in what the Bible calls a “bond of peace.”
2人は結ばれていたのです
ですから 友情に少しひびが入っても
So even though their friendship
experienced strain,
2人の絆が強かったので
すぐに関係を修復することができました
the bond between them was strong
—strong enough to withstand the stress.
では現代に当てはめましょう
Well, let’s bring this to our day.
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオの中で ある長老は
どのように平和の種をまくでしょうか
please notice how an elder sows peace.
But you know, there is more to the story.
この話には続きがあって
フィルは知らなかったんですが
Phil didn’t know just
ティムとの関係が
険悪になっちゃったんです
how tense things were between Tim and I.
No idea.
知りませんでした
We never talked,
もっと穏やかに
I mean really talked, about it
話していればよかったんです
until it was too late.
ああなる前に
Look!
カール
We need to talk.
ちょっと話があるんですけど
I think we need to seriously reconsider
Phil’s qualifications.
フィルの資格 再検討しないと
いけないんじゃないですか
You know he’s not
the type of brother that . . .
フィルはあんな兄弟じゃないって・・・
いや いや もうフィルのことはいい
友達だからそう言っているんだろ・・・
Enough. Enough!
Enough about Phil.
I know he’s your friend, . . .
Friend?
友達？
. . . but the body agreed that he
no longer qualified to serve as an elder.
長老団はフィルには長老としての
資格がないと決めたんだ
Friend?
He’s worked with us for years!
友達？友達って 一緒に何年も
働いてきた仲じゃないですか
The body decided, unanimously,
長老団は全員一致で
資格がないと決めたんだ
that he should no longer serve.
カールが圧力をかけたから
じゃないですか！
Because you pushed them!
なんだって？
Excuse me?
It’s enough that we have
those outside the congregation
世の人からの反対がある上に
会衆の中でそんな圧力をかけて
どうするんですか！
putting pressure on us;
we do not need more in here!
Do you seriously think . . .
本気でそんなことを？
The conversation
—the argument—
話し合いというより
けんかになって ひどかった
it was terrible.
2人とも言い過ぎてしまった
We both said things we didn’t mean.
And after that,
we both handled the situation poorly.
その後の対応も良くなかった
We needed to make things right.
なんとかする必要があった
It wasn’t easy,
簡単ではなかったけど
but we talked it out.
きちんと話し合った
And we made peace with Jehovah’s help.
エホバの助けで
仲直りできた
Can you imagine what it would have been like
in that cellblock if we hadn’t?
そうしていなかったら
刑務所の中でどうなっていたんだろうね
We finally told Phil the whole story
once we were all roommates.
みんなと同じ監房に入れられてから
さっきのことをフィルに話したんだ
Wow!
そうだったんですか
We’re ready!
歌うよ！
Let’s go sing.
行こうか
Like an island of calm
In dark stormy seas,
この世界がどんよりと暗く沈んでも
God’s people are living in peace.
With our eyes of faith,
We see beyond the clouds
信仰の目には見える 明るい未来が
And know that the storm soon will cease.
To the ends of the earth,
There’ll be peace at last
川を越えて山も越え その向こうまで
For all eternity.
From the valleys below . . .
この地球の果てにまで⋯⋯
では長老の皆さん
次の点を考えましょう
Elders, here’s the question
before all of us now:
How can we imitate Paul and Barnabas?
どうすればパウロとバルナバに
倣えるでしょうか
First, as elders,
we must apply Scriptural counsel
まず 仲間の長老たちに接する時にも
聖書の教えを当てはめる必要があります
in our dealings with one another.
In the video, we just saw how imperfection
got the better of Tim and Carl
ビデオの中で ティムとカールは
激しくぶつかっていましたね
—their body language,
choice of words, tone of voice.
それが身振りや言葉や口調に
表れていました
ティムは「けんかになって
ひどかった」と言っていました
As Tim put it,
‘The argument was terrible.’
But after the dispute,
でもけんかの後 2人はやがて
どんな正しいことをしましたか
what did those two elders
eventually do right?
They applied Scriptural counsel
and made peace.
聖書の教えを当てはめて
仲直りしました
ヤコブ 3:17は 私たち皆が
For example, the divine counsel at James 3:17
「平和を求め 分別」を示す
必要があると教えています
reminds all of us
to be “peaceable [and] reasonable.”
The Watchtower {
この点が以前の「ものみの塔」誌に
次のように説明されていました
I quote: “Peacemakers
modestly express their thoughts
「平和を作る人は
慎み深く自分の考えを述べ
“and then respectfully listen
to those of others.
敬意を込めて人の考えに
耳を傾けます ⋯⋯
“Instead of insisting on his own way,
自分のやり方にこだわらず
“a peacemaker will prayerfully consider
his brother’s viewpoint.
他の兄弟の見解を
祈りのうちに考慮します
たいていの場合
聖書の原則に反しないで
“If no Bible principle is violated,
“there is usually room
for varied points of view.
さまざまな見方を入れる
余地があるものです ⋯⋯
“Experienced overseers
know that preserving the peace
経験のある監督は 平和を保つほうが
自分の思い通りに事を運ぶより
重要であることを心得ています」
is more important
than getting one’s own way.”
当てはめたいですね
What a beautiful thought!
では 1つ目の点として
So, what’s our first lesson?
If we as elders apply Scriptural counsel
仲間の長老と接する時にも
ぜひ聖書の教えを当てはめましょう
in our dealings with one another,
we’ll never allow a difference of opinion
to become a cause for animosity.
そうすれば 意見が合わなくても
対立してしまうことはないでしょう
ローマ 12:10に
学べる2つ目の点が書かれているので
Romans 12:10 outlines a second lesson.
Please open your Bible with me there.
そこを開いて読んでみましょう
Under inspiration, at Romans 12:10,
ここで使徒パウロは 神の聖なる力に
導かれて次のように書きました
Paul wrote this:
「兄弟愛を抱いて
“In brotherly love
“have tender affection for one another.
優しい愛情を示し合いましょう
自分の方から進んで
人を敬ってください」
In showing honor to one another,
take the lead.”
長老の皆さん
終わりの時代である今こそ
Brothers (elders), now,
before life gets even more difficult,
私たちはこのことを行う必要があります
this is what we need to do.
We need to strengthen
love and affection for one another.
互いへの愛をますます強くする
必要があるのです
そのために 誰と話していても
We can do that by continuing to speak well
仲間の長老をけなしたりせず
褒めるようにしましょう
of our fellow elders
in public and in private,
by resisting the urge to talk negatively
to other elders
意見が合わなくても 腹を立てたり
強い言葉を使ったりしないようにします
about any disagreements that arise,
and by regularly reflecting
on our brothers’ good qualities
仲間の長老の良いところや
一緒に奉仕してきた楽しい思い出に
ついて 思い起こすようにしましょう
and on our past service together.
In the video, weren’t we happy
to see how Tim and Carl
ビデオの中で ティムとカールが
パウロとバルナバに倣い
imitated Paul and Barnabas
and eventually reaped peace?
平和を刈り取ることができて
本当に良かったですね
簡単ではありませんでしたが
Though not easy,
they applied Scriptural counsel
聖書の教えを当てはめて
仲直りできました
and resolved their problem.
カールはティムの家を訪ねた時
That warm smile on Carl’s face
when he showed up at Tim’s home,
笑顔を浮かべていました
the dessert (perhaps Tim’s favorite pie),
お土産はティムの大好きな
パイだったかもしれません
腹を割って話し合いました
the heart-to-heart talk,
and their lasting friendship, even in prison,
そして 刑務所に入った後も
友情が続いていました
showed that they maintained
their love and affection for each other.
ですから 互いへの強い愛を
保っていたことがよく分かります
Dear brothers, elders, may we do likewise.
長老の皆さん 私たちもぜひ
そうありたいものですね
仲たがいをしても
速やかに解決しましょう
Let’s settle disagreements
quickly and peacefully.
When we do so, we’ll reap not only peace,
そうすれば
平和を刈り取れるだけでなく
パウロとバルナバのように
but we’ll prove to be examples to the flock,
群れの模範になることが
できるに違いありません
just like Paul and Barnabas.
Brother Stephen Lett,
a member of the Governing Body,
統治体のスティーブン・レット兄弟が
このシンポジウムの
最後の話をしてくださいます
will now consider the final talk
of this symposium,
主題は 「平和の種をまいて
平和を刈り取った人たち 現代の例」
“How They Sowed and Reaped Peace
—Modern-Day Examples.”
世の中の不正を目にしたとき
How do many people react
when they see corruption and injustice?
多くの人はどのように
反応するでしょうか
怒りを感じて
どうにかしたいと思います
They become incensed,
and they want to fix the problem.
How do they try to fix the problem?
それでどうしますか
政治的な活動を行ったり
社会運動に加わったりして
By becoming involved
in political efforts or social movements
政治の腐敗や社会の不正を
正そうとします
that claim to fight corruption and injustice.
In contrast,
対照的に エホバの証人は
政治活動や社会運動に加わりません
why do Jehovah’s Witnesses not get involved
in political efforts or social movements?
どうしてでしょうか 簡単に言うと
The simple answer is
because they’ve learned from God’s Word
今の世の中の問題は
人間の力では正せないことを
that the problems of this world
cannot be corrected.
聖書から学んで知っているからです
伝道の書 1:15には
Ecclesiastes 1:15 says:
「曲がっているものは真っすぐに
できない」と書かれています
“What is crooked cannot be made straight.”
サタンの世の中は 非常に曲がり
くねって節くれ立った木の幹のように
Satan’s world around us
is like the trunk of a tree
that has grown so crooked, twisted, gnarled
人間の力では決して
真っすぐにすることはできないのです
that it cannot be made straight.
Jehovah’s Witnesses have learned
ですから エホバが正せないと言って
いるさまざまな問題を正そうとして
that it would be futile
to spend our time and energy
trying to correct what Jehovah tells us
cannot be corrected.
時間や労力を費やすことには
あまり意味がありません
Additionally, Jehovah’s Witnesses
have learned how and where
さらに エホバの証人は
問題だらけの世の中でも
平和や安心感を味わえるということを
学んできました
real peace can be found even now.
In this regard,
ではこの点で 現代の2つの例を
考えてみましょう
let’s consider two modern-day examples
of ones who came
to acquire Jehovah’s thinking
平和についてのエホバの考えを
学ぶことができた2人の人の例です
on this matter.
Let’s talk about Egidio Nahakbria
その人たちの名前は
エジディオ･ナハクブリアと
and Frede Bruun.
フリード･ブルーンです
Now, first Egidio
まずエジディオの例です
—born in a remote part of East Timor,
東ティモールのへき地で
生まれたエジディオは
he experienced horrible
guerrilla warfare during his childhood.
子供の頃に悲惨なゲリラ戦を
経験しました
近所の人たちが何人も殺されたので
次は自分かもしれないと思いました
Many of his neighbors
disappeared or were killed,
and he feared he would be next.
でも しばらくたってから
首都に引っ越して大学に入り
But some years later,
he moved to the capital city
and entered a university
そこで同じような境遇で育った
たくさんの学生と出会いました
where he met many other youths
with backgrounds similar to his.
He became part of a student group
that was trying to achieve social change
エジディオたちは 政治活動をする
学生のグループをつくって
社会改革を目指しました
through political action.
学生たちで政治デモを
何度も行いましたが
Many political demonstrations were organized,
but most ended up in riots,
大抵の場合 暴動に発展しました
多くの友人が負傷し
命を落とした人もいます
with many of his friends injured.
Some were even killed.
後に エジディオは親戚と一緒に
エホバの証人から聖書を学び始めました
But then through a relative
who was studying with Jehovah’s Witnesses,
Egidio started to study.
Now, here’s what he said
as he started this study:
その時の心境についてこう語っています
「聖書を学ぶにつれ
“As I studied the Bible,
“I began to feel that I had
never really known love.
本当の愛を知らなかったことに
気づきました⋯⋯
わたしの近寄りがたい風貌や
乱暴な気質にもかかわらず
“Despite my rough
appearance and disposition,
“the Witnesses treated me
with ‘fellow feeling’
証人たちは⋯⋯『兄弟の愛情』を
示してくれました」
and ‘brotherly affection.’”
Well, soon he was baptized,
became a regular pioneer,
間もなくエジディオは
バプテスマを受けました
and he was so happy because now he knew
そして開拓者になって
多くの人たちを助けるようになりました
he was truly helping people.
He ended his life story with these words:
ライフ･ストーリーの結びで
次のように述べています
「以前のわたしは怒りに満ち
“In the past,
I felt angry, unloved, and unlovable.
自分は愛されていない 愛される
価値もないと感じていました
“But thanks to Jehovah,
でも エホバのおかげで 真の愛と
安らぎを見いだすことができました」
at last I have found true love and peace!”
次はフリードの例です
But now let’s talk about Frede.
From an early age,
he was very upset
フリードは幼い頃から 世の中の
憎しみや争いに心を痛めていました
by all the hatred, bloodshed,
and war he saw around him.
特に 宗教が行ってきたことに
But especially was he disturbed
by religion’s role in all of this.
とても当惑していました
He observed that much
of this hatred, bloodshed, and war
憎しみや争いが多くの場合
宗教によって助長され 支持され
was encouraged, supported,
or at least condoned by religion.
少なくとも大目に見られてきたからです
But in 1955, he attended
a convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
1955年 フリードは
エホバの証人の大会に行きました
And after the convention,
he accepted a Bible study.
その後 エホバの証人と
聖書を学ぶようになりました
Now, during his studies,
he learned many wonderful things,
いろいろな良いことを学びましたが
特に心を動かされたことがありました
but something he learned
really motivated him.
それは 「大娼婦」つまり大いなる
バビロンの実体を知ったことです
He learned the identity
of the “great prostitute,”
Babylon the Great,
その大娼婦は
啓示 17, 18章に出てきます
mentioned in Revelation chapters 17 and 18.
He learned that this prostitute
その大娼婦が表しているのは 世界を
惑わしている間違った宗教全体です
is the world empire of false religion.
説明されてとりわけ印象に残ったのは
啓示 18:24でした
Then he was really amazed
when he was shown Revelation 18:24,
which says:
“In her [the prostitute] was found the blood
そこには 「彼女
［つまり大娼婦］の中には ⋯⋯
地上で殺された全ての人の血が
見いだされました」と書かれています
of all those
who have been slaughtered on the earth.”
それでフリードは 間違った宗教は
So he learned that the world’s religions
決して国際的な平和を
もたらせないことを理解しました
could never be a force
for international peace
そうした宗教は政治を支持し
分裂していて 戦争をするからです
because they take sides,
they’re divided,
and they go to war.
In contrast,
he saw that Jehovah’s Witnesses
対照的に エホバの証人は
国を超えた家族のような関係で
are an international brotherhood
イエスの教え通りに
行動していることが分かりました
that truly practices what Jesus taught.
Frede’s progress was very fast.
フリードは急速に進歩しました
バプテスマを受け 開拓者になり
ギレアデ学校に行きました
He got baptized, started pioneering,
attended the 50th class of Gilead,
そして 長年グアテマラで奉仕し
多くの人たちを助けてきました
and has served many years in Guatemala,
helping people (as he was helped)
to find the true Source of peace.
本当の平和をどうすれば見いだせるかを
教えてきたのです
But now we ask,
では エジディオとフリードの例から
私たちはどんなことを学べるでしょうか
What are lessons we can learn
from Egidio and Frede?
主に3つの点を考えましょう
1つ目です
Well, many,
but here are three big ones.
Number one:
We can never correct the corruption
政治の腐敗や社会の不正は
政治活動や社会運動では
and injustice of this world
by means of political efforts
or social movements.
決して正すことができない という
ことを覚えておきましょう
That reminds me
of the illustration a brother used
こんな例えを聞いたことがあります
ある人が必死にクモの巣を
取り除こうとしますが
about trying to get rid of a problem
with spiderwebs but being unable
to get rid of the spider.
クモを退治することができません
You knock the webs down;
クモの巣を取っても
すぐにまたクモが作るという繰り返しで
the spider builds them right back.
You knock them down;
it builds them back.
問題が解決しません
You never get rid of the problem.
サタンはいわば この例えの中に
出てくるクモのようです
Well, in this illustration,
Satan is the spider.
And since he’s the source
of corruption and injustice,
サタンが腐敗や不正の根本原因なので
サタンがいる限り問題は解決しません
as long as he exists,
the problem will exist.
Little puny humans can’t get rid of Satan.
人間にはサタンを退治できません
ずっと強いからです
He’s superhuman,
解決には 人間より
ずっと強い力が必要です
so the solution must also be superhuman.
その力を持っているのが神の王国です
And that’s where God’s Kingdom comes in.
神の王国は クモの巣のような
問題を取り除くだけでなく
God’s Kingdom can and will
not only get rid of the webs
but the old spider Satan himself too.
クモであるサタン自身も
取り除くことができます
では2つ目の点です
Now here’s our second lesson:
We must remember that political activism
政治デモなどは多くの場合
暴力的な活動に発展します
often leads to violence,
which is the opposite of peace.
暴力は平和とは正反対のものです
We pursue peace
—don’t we?—
私たちが追い求めるのは平和であって
not conduct that often leads to violence.
暴力などではありません
Our third lesson:
3つ目の点です
ほかのいろいろな宗教とは違って
Unlike the religions of this world,
エホバの証人はあらゆる人と
平和な関係でいることを望んでいます
we must promote peace with all people,
which definitely means
we refuse to get involved in any way
ですから サタンの世の中の
さまざまな争いで
どちらかの側に付くことは
決してしません
in the wars of Satan’s world.
That reminds me of an experience
a young brother had in the ministry.
ある若い兄弟の伝道での経験を
思い出します
ある女性が感情的にこう言いました
A very emotional woman said to him:
「あなたが自由を味わえるのも
“My son died
私の息子が戦争で戦って死んだからよ
“for you to have the freedom you have.
Why won’t you fight for your country?”
あなたは国のために戦わないの？」
兄弟は穏やかにこう言いました
Well, very calmly,
the young brother said:
「息子さんが亡くなられたことは
本当に残念です
“I’m very sorry
about the loss of your dear son.
“But one thing I can guarantee you
でも1つ言えることがあります
“is that it was not
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
あなたの息子さんを殺したのは
絶対にエホバの証人ではありません
“who killed your son.
ほかの宗教はどうか分かりませんが
エホバの証人は人を殺しません」
“Now, I don’t know if you can make
that guarantee about your religion,
but I can make that guarantee.”
カトリックだったその女性は
Well, as it turned out,
she was Catholic,
エホバの証人が中立であることを
理解したことでしょう
so she definitely was unable
to make that guarantee.
So let’s remember
these three powerful lessons
では 今考えた3つの大切な点を
覚えておくようにしましょう
that we have discussed.
この大会を視聴している
聖書に関心がある皆さん
But now we’d like to say
to you dear interested ones in attendance,
もしまだ聖書レッスンをしていないなら
if you’re not yet one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we warmly invite you to please
ぜひエホバの証人と聖書を
学んでみることを心からお勧めします
study the Bible with us.
本当の愛を表すことが最高の
生き方であることが分かるでしょう
See for yourself how genuine love
is the best way of life
社会を分裂させているさまざまな
問題も 愛があれば乗り越えられます
and is the best way to deal with the problems
that divide society today.
イエスがはっきり述べた通り
Jesus made it crystal clear
that the identifying mark
of true Christians is love.
真のクリスチャンを
見分けるしるしは 愛です
At John 13:35, he said:
ヨハネ 13:35には
“By this all will know
that you are my disciples
「あなたたちの間に愛があれば
全ての人は
あなたたちが私の弟子であることを
知ります」とあります
—if you have love among yourselves.”
So dear interested ones,
聖書に関心がある皆さん
この本物の愛が
see for yourself whether this genuine love
エホバの証人の間に見られるかどうか
ぜひ確かめてください
exists among Jehovah’s Witnesses.
すでにエホバの証人である皆さんは
何ができるでしょうか
But now we say to those of you
who are already Jehovah’s Witnesses,
please continue to cultivate and show
ぜひ「信仰で結ばれた兄弟たち
全員を愛」するように
“love for the whole association of brothers.”
引き続き努力を払ってください
And doing so will require
that you remain strictly neutral
そのためには 世の中の政治的な事柄や
他のさまざまな問題において
regarding the world’s political affairs
and other controversies,
いつも中立の立場を取る必要があります
just as our Leader remained neutral.
イエスがいつも中立だったようにです
At John 17:14,
Jesus said of his disciples:
ヨハネ 17:14で
イエスは弟子たちについて
「私が世の人々のようでは
ないのと同じように
“They are no part of the world,
just as I am no part of the world.”
彼らも世の人々のようでは
ない」と言いました
So during discussions in the ministry
or anywhere for that matter,
では 伝道で人と話す時であれ
ほかのどんな時であれ
remain strictly neutral
政治的な事柄については
いつも中立を保つようにしましょう
on political topics.
Take no position regarding what laws
should be enacted,
こういう法律を作った方がいい
なくした方がいい
変えた方がいい などと
言ってはなりません
repealed, or changed.
自分の見方を他の人に
押し付けるべきでもありません
And don’t pressure others
to agree with your view.
But to succeed in this,
中立を保つために大事なこととして
we must be careful not to allow
the media of this world
自分の考えがメディアの影響を
受けないように注意しましょう
to manipulate our thinking.
ニュース報道には偏った見方が
表れていることが少なくありません
News broadcasts are often presented
in a biased, opinionated way.
So we’ve got to be careful
not to adopt the bias of a commentator.
ですから うのみにするべきでは
ありません
考え方の面で中立であるなら
Only if we keep our thinking neutral
言葉や行動においても
中立であることができます
will we be able to keep
our speech and actions neutral also.
もし皆さんがクリスチャンとして
中立の立場を貫くなら
And remember, your good example
of showing love in Christian neutrality
may attract honest-hearted ones to the truth.
誠実な人たちが真理に
引き寄せられるかもしれません
私たちはこのシンポジウムを通して
どんなことを学べたでしょうか
But now we ask,
What have we learned from this symposium?
それぞれの部分で学んだ要点を
1つずつ思い起こしてみましょう
Well, let’s highlight just one
valuable takeaway lesson
from each of our six parts.
1つ目の話は「ヨセフと兄たち」でした
The first part,
“Joseph and His Brothers”:
Our lesson is sow peace
要点は 憤りの気持ちを捨て去ることに
よって平和の種をまくことができます
by letting go of resentment.
2つ目の話は「ギベオンの人たち」
The second part,
“The Gibeonites”:
Humbly submit to Jehovah’s will,
自分の望んでいることと違ったとしても
even if it differs from what you prefer.
謙遜にエホバの指示に
従うことが大切です
3つ目は「ギデオン」
The third part,
“Gideon”:
不和が深刻な問題に発展しないように
Prevent conflicts from escalating
よく考えられた快い言葉を
語るように努力できます
by choosing words that calm,
reassure, and heal.
The fourth part,
“Abigail”:
4つ目は「アビガイル」
平和をつくるためにベストを尽くして
Do what you can to promote peace,
後はエホバに委ねることにしましょう
and then leave matters with Jehovah.
5つ目は「メピボセテ」
The fifth part,
“Mephibosheth”:
被害を受けたままにする方が
Be willing to suffer loss
会衆の平和を乱すより
良い場合があります
rather than disturb the peace
in the congregation.
この点に少し付け加えると
And just another thought on this:
Let’s always remember
自分の名誉よりも エホバの評判を
守ることの方がはるかに大事です
that defending Jehovah’s name and reputation
is far more important
そのことをいつも
忘れないようにしましょう
than trying to defend
our own name and reputation.
Be willing to suffer loss
ですから 自分のことよりも
rather than disturb the peace
in the congregation.
会衆の平和を守る方が
よい場合があるのです
そして この話は「現代の例」でした
The sixth part (this part),
“Modern-Day Examples”:
Serve the God of peace with his people,
神の民と共に平和の神に仕えるなら
平和を味わうことができます
and you will have peace.
このシンポジウムを通して
どうすれば平和の種をまけるか
Yes, during this symposium,
we’ve learned many valuable lessons
as to how we can sow peace.
多くの点を学べました
Let’s all be determined to do so
with all our heart.
ぜひ平和の種をまき続けましょう
And what will be the final result?
そうするとどうなるでしょうか
For the answer,
答えは このシンポジウムの
最後のビデオを見ると分かります
let’s watch the final dramatization
of this symposium.
ご一緒に見ましょう
私も話したいことがあります
There’s one more story to tell.
まだ気付いていなかったのですが
I didn’t know it at the time,
but seeds of truth
私の心に真理の種がまかれていたんです
were being planted in my heart.
You were all so different.
皆さんは明らかに違っていました
I couldn’t understand it.
なぜだろう と思いました
You were prisoners, yes,
刑務所にいるのに
皆さん自由に見えました
but you felt free
そんなのは初めて見ました
—truly free.
After you were released,
皆さんが釈放されてから
皆さんには神の祝福があったんだ
ということがはっきり分かりました
it became clear to me
that you have God’s blessing,
and I wanted to know why.
その違いはなんだろう と思いました
Phil helped me find the answer.
フィルが答えを教えてくれました
“And you will know the truth,
「真理を知り
and the truth will set you free.”
真理によって自由になります」
フィルは 真理に従って生きるよう
勧めてくれました
Phil encouraged me to make the truth my own.
I had real trouble at first.
最初は難しく感じました
With all the turmoil going on at the time,
世界がひどく混乱しているのに
the idea of being peaceable
平和を貫き神の王国を待つ
という感覚が
and waiting on God’s Kingdom
—it was hard to grasp.
どうしても分かりませんでした
But with Jehovah’s help
でも エホバの助けと
and the patience of these good people,
皆さんの辛抱のおかげで
大患難が始まる前に
I was baptized
before the start of the great tribulation.
バプテスマを受けることができました
Joseph, during our time in prison,
ヨセフ 私たちは投獄された時
the story of your life
牢屋に入れられても
エホバがいつも共にいたという
—your time in prison
あなたの話から
本当に力をもらっていたんですよ
and how Jehovah was always with you—
became a real source of strength
for us.
I remember one day,
ある時カール 言ってましたよね
Carl said—
What did you say?
なんでしたっけ？
I said, “One day,
we’ll have a meal with Joseph,
「いつかヨセフを呼んで食事会をして
and we’ll say ‘thank you.’”
みんなで『ありがとう』って言おう」
実現してうれしいです
And here we are!
Really, it’s I who should thank you.
いや 感謝したいのは私の方です
Each and every one
of your stories
皆さんのそれぞれの話を聞いて
感動しました
touches my heart.
You know a lot about my life,
皆さん 私のこと
よく知っていると思いますけど
but would it be all right
if I shared a few more stories?
もう少しお話ししてもいいですか
Please!
ぜひ！たくさん聞きたいことあります
We have so many questions.
エジプトのこととか
Can you tell us about Egypt?
ファラオどんな人でした？
What was Pharaoh really like?
Dreams!
あ 夢！夢のことも聞かなくっちゃ
We have to talk about those dreams.
You do have many questions!
ほんとにたくさん質問あるんですね
And I have many details to share.
いくらでも喜んでお話ししますよ
神エホバに感謝すべきことに
And thanks to our God, Jehovah,
we have all the time we need.
時間はたっぷりありますからね
感動的なビデオでした
What a touching video!
一生懸命に平和の種をまくなら
If we wholeheartedly sow peace,
私たちは自分自身や他の人たちを
救うことになります
we’ll ‘save ourselves
and those who listen to us.’
But what fundamental truth from our great God
このシンポジウムを通して
聖書のどんな基本的な真理について
学べたでしょうか
have we discussed during this symposium?
It’s expressed at Galatians 6:7:
それはガラテア 6:7に
書かれていることです
「人は自分がまいているものを
“For whatever a person is sowing,
this he will also reap.”
必ず刈り取ることになります」
If we sow a tomato seed,
例えば トマトの種をまいたら
必ずトマトを刈り取れます
we will always get tomato plants.
この基本的な真理は
平和にも当てはまります
Well, this unfailing fundamental truth
applies to peace.
If we sow peace,
we will always reap peace.
平和の種をまくなら
必ず平和を刈り取れます
Although in some cases,
もちろん 平和の種をまいてから
it may take some time
for the peace we sowed to bring good results.
平和を刈り取るまでに
時間がかかる場合もあるでしょう
でも粘り強く平和の種をまくなら
But if we persevere in sowing peace,
we will reap peace of mind,
私たちは心の平和や
他の人たちとの平和 そして
エホバとの平和な関係を刈り取れます
peace with others and, most important,
peace with Jehovah.
And we’ll reap the reward
of living forever in a world
また 永遠に生きるという
報いも刈り取り
平和に満ちた世界で
いつまでも幸せに暮らせます
where there will be an abundance of peace.
So let’s be determined to sow peace now
平和の種をまくべきなのは今です
そうすれば 将来ずっと
平和を刈り取れるのです
so that we can reap peace forever.
And if you think about it,
that’s a pretty good investment
of our time and effort, isn’t it?
時間や労力を費やす
価値があると言えますね
Sow peace now
では 今平和の種をまいて
and reap peace forever.
永遠にわたって平和を刈り取りましょう
Thank you, brothers,
for those practical talks.
兄弟たち ありがとうございました
話で取り上げられた良い手本に倣い
May we all remember these useful examples
今平和の種をまいて 永遠にわたって
平和を刈り取りたいと思います
and sow peace now
so that we can reap peace eternally.
Let’s sing together song number 28,
では 28番の歌を歌いましょう
“Gaining Jehovah’s Friendship.”
主題は「エホバの友となる」です
歌は28番です
That’s song number 28.